<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the recantation of Iohn Nichols (for the space almost of two yeeres the Popes scholer in the English Seminarie or Colledge at Rome) which desireth to be reconciled and receiued as a member into the true Church of Christ in England.</title>
            <author>Nicholls, John, 1555-1584?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18533.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900381</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2012:4, 325:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the recantation of Iohn Nichols (for the space almost of two yeeres the Popes scholer in the English Seminarie or Colledge at Rome) which desireth to be reconciled and receiued as a member into the true Church of Christ in England.</title>
                  <author>Nicholls, John, 1555-1584?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[196] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1581. Februarii. 14.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M N² .</note>
                  <note>The title page is in two settings: line above imprint has (1) "God: Honour" (reel 325:12) or (2) "God : Honour" (reel 2012:4). Quire N is in two settings: N1r, line 3 from bottom ends (1) "from" (both reel positions) or (2) "frō". The first eight lines of L1r are in three settings: first line begins (1) "tichrist", (2) "ry", or (3) "gory"; the last setting is the correct one.</note>
                  <note>Identified on film as STC 18533.5, at reel 2012.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 2012:4 lacks final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge, England, and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Identified by ESTC as STC (2nd ed.) 18533.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A declaration</hi> of the recantation of Iohn Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chols (for the ſpace almoſt of two yeeres the Popes Scholer in the Engliſh Seminarie or Colledge at Rome) which deſireth to be reconciled and receiued as a member into the true Church of Chriſt in England.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>1 Eſdr. 4.38, 41.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Magna eſt veritas &amp; praualet.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Tertul. de virginibus.</bibl>
                     <p>Whatſoeuer ſauoreth againſt the truth, is an hereſie, be it neuer ſo ancient a cuſtome.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>1. Peter 2.17.</bibl>
                     <p>Feare God: Honour the King.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Imprinted at London <hi>by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer</hi> to the Queenes moſt excellent <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anno 1581. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarii. 14.</p>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>decorative border incorporating the royal English blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Illuſtri Equiti, clariſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moque <hi>Regiae Maieſtatis</hi> Londini Caſtrorum praeſidi, <hi>cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dique inſigni, praestanti, ac nobilitate verae</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae, &amp; virtutis inſignibus decorato, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino <hi>Odoeno Hopton, domino ſuo obſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> Iohannes Nicholaus gratiam &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem a Deo patre, &amp; a Domino noſtro Ieſu Chriſto.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>ATER ille coeleſtis (vir praestantiſſime, omni pietatis, atque religionis genere perpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite &amp; exculte) ſic mei peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentis papiſtici erroris tabe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè conſumpti, &amp; ab omni ferè virtute remoti tandem miſertus eſt, vt ex denſiſſima mortis caligine, atque profunda ignorantiae abyſſo, me ſibi ingratum &amp; inobedientem filium eruere dignaretur: atque in ſuae eccleſiae,<note place="margin">Luk.
15.20, 21.</note> nullis ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolatriae ſordibus maculatae, gremium reuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non negaret: &amp; omnimoda bonarum lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum eruditione refertos, ſatiſque ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis notis cumulatos viros excitaret, qui ſuo fraterno labore &amp; induſtria, contenderent quàm maximè poſſent, in Christi Euangelicae veritatis agnitionem me demùm vendicare:
<pb facs="tcp:176510:3"/> quorum incorruptis, nullis hypocriſews inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucris, &amp; integumentis, documentis, praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſquè inuolutis imbutus ac inſtructus, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum (inquam) conſilio fretus, &amp; ſuffultus, (di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uina illa gratia animum meum ad bonita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem diſponente) non ambigo, neque animi pendeo, me poſſe cauſam meae religionis ſuſcipere, tueri ac defendere, in conspectu illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aduerſariorum, quos aliquandiu diurna co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſortij familiaritas mihi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignotos fecit. Ea ſunt Dei omnipotentis in me collocata bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia, quae enumerando percenſere, &amp; expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando conſequi non eſt mearum virium. Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando fediſſimae orationis, vanitatis &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantiae ſeruituti mancipatus eram: iam verò omnis mendacij &amp; inſcitiae obſcuritate noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teque fugata, clariſſimum mihi veritatis lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men affulget: ingenium meum antehàc adèo deprauatum, &amp; a verbo Dei alienum erat, vt maiori delectatione, atque vehementiori deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derio, hominum commentitias traditiones ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs approbarem et amplecterer, quàm profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem illam Catholicam, quam Chriſti Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli tradiderunt, martyres ſuo ſanguine effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confirmauerunt, &amp; fideles hucuſque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant, amplexibus exciperem, ſinuque foue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem: Nunc verò ingenio meo Spiritus ſancti flamme accenſo &amp; inflammato (depulſis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis <pb facs="tcp:176510:3"/> erroribus, quibus conſtrictus &amp; irretitus fueram,) Sathanae impoſturas intelligentia &amp; ratione comprehendo, falſae opinionis tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras ab oculis depello, (auxilio diuino mihi ſuffragante) &amp; ſalutarem Euangelij verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem magno cum amore proſequi incipio. Ante hoc conuerſionis meae tempus, verbo Dei au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res erant mihi clauſae, vt illud audire abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerem, atque reclamarem, in me caecitas ita dominatum habuit, vt fulgentes Christi E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelij radios videre aspernarer. Iam duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore Spiritu ſancto, atque atroci conſcientiae vulnere ſtimulatus, animaduerto Papista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fabulas prorſus incerto niti fundamento, illorúmque religionem non modò nulla affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re conſcientiae multis delictis obrutae &amp; cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunceſſae efficacia medicamenta, verùm eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am altiùs tela infligere, animam, (vitae pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam cauſam) diris infaustíſque vinculis at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que compedibus arctare &amp; constringere, &amp; planè apertéque Deo eiuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> verbo vim infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Turpia illorum idola, craſſiſſimi errores, blaſphemiae infinitae, ſuperſtitiones deteſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, vaniſſima commenta, ac denique vitae inaudita &amp; horrenda turpitudo, atque dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus ob oculos mihi verſantur. Meditor ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> cogito quantis quam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> varijs aſtutijs &amp; blandimentis, homines cuncti doli frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſque <pb facs="tcp:176510:4"/> expertes, immuneſque, verſuti Papiſtae alliciunt atque titillant, ad ſuam pernitioſam doctrinam amplexanda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ad hos praefatos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines deludendos, &amp; in ſempiternam fraude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conijciendos, in angelos ſe lucis tranſferunt, &amp; eam vitae exteriorem pietatem prae ſe ferunt, qua faciliùs incautoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominum mentes cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuenire queant. Sed plus gloria &amp; praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione ſua bona opera (ſi bona dici poſſint) efferunt, atque extollunt, quàm veritas conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poſſit. Non verentur illi (omnibus pudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris velis reuulſis, cunctoque dei altitonantis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more depoſito, omnique charitatisnota relega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; in exilium pulſa) dicere illos coelitum dignitatem, moribus &amp; institutis, atque vitae ſanctimonia conſecutos. O impudentes Pàpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas, mendacij ſordibus illinitos, &amp; omni ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi funestae prauitati ſuccumbentes, atque à fide Chriſtiana, &amp; charitate fraterna auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos! Quotus enim quiſque inter vos vitam non degit belluinam? Quis Dominum timet? Quis illum diligit? Quis pietatis ruinas ede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re formidat? Quis inter vos (vt breui com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendam) fontem aquae vitae non deſerit, &amp; ciſternas ſibi fodit maximè diſſipatas?<note place="margin">Iere.
2.13.</note> Si quorundam Papiſtarum vitam, omnium ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerum, libidinúmque maculis notiſſimam, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinis verbis explicare conarer, Latinae linguae <pb facs="tcp:176510:4"/> rudes nihil inde fructus perciperent, quia quod diceretur, neutiquam intelligeretur. Qua de cauſa operaepretium me facturum duxi, ſi nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ac impolita (bona tamen cum fide, animó<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſyncero) exarata narratione beneuolo Lectori ſatisfacerem, lingua nostra Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana narrando &amp; exponendo ea, quae vidi at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que audiui à viris fide dignis inter illos geſta. Praeterea nostros ſacrificulos Romani Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis (filij perditionis) mandato miſſos &amp; dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatos in hanc florentiſſimam Angliae Inſulam ad peruertendos huius terrae accolas, &amp; veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſplendori inſidiantes, quo ſtudio perpetuò tenebras moliuntur in hoc regnum reducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, quas huic ſolo ſuo paterno minas commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur, atque quibus conuitijs optimos quoſque viros inſectantur, in hac epistola dedicatoria ſilentio praeteribo. De Papistis ſatis hoc in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co verba feciſſe videor, &amp; hinc te (vir clariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime, religione, iuſticia, liberalitate, caeterìſque heroicis animi dotibus nobiliter ſtipate &amp; vallate) hac oratione craſſo filo mihi ſcripta affari liceat, cui inter homines mortales plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimum debere, ac cui ob tuam erga me cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem, ad extremum vitae anhelitum me obstrictum ſentio, deuinctum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fateor. (Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da abſit verbo vanitas.) Quem laborem pro me, cùm verae Eccleſiae ſeptis non tenebar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſus <pb facs="tcp:176510:5"/> ſuſcepisti, omnibus patefacia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cùm fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram carceribus dete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus, eò quòd in Papistaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partem propendebam, (&amp; in <hi>Seminario An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicano,</hi> Romae duos (plus minus) annos ſede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> collocaſſem, quàm ſaepe me ad te accerſi voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ríque fecisti, quàm manſuetè humanitérque mecum ſemper egisti, quàm ſalubre mihi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium impertitus es, vt Papisticae idololatriae faecem exuerem! nonne concionatores per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multos, non vulgari doctrina praeditos ad me accedere voluiſti? vt ſi qua poſſent ratione, me coeleſti Euangelij veritati reconciliarent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que deuincirent. Pleroſque mihi inſuper li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros ſuppeditaſti, quibus nonnunquam lectis, immenſo Dei beneficio, magnam inde vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem ſalutiferam mihi (paruo temporis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriecto ſpatio) comparaui. Habito identidem ſermone cum peritis, atque crebris concioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus auditis, ex indubiae veritatis inimico (Deo adiuuante) dum in his incluſus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris compagibus fuero, verum meipſum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabo amicum, &amp; ad ſtudia ſacrarum litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum animum applicabo, quarum praeſidio, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistarum fraudes detegere, &amp; furta conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere valeam, &amp; omnibus (Deo meis conatibus auspicante) demonſtrabo, quod ſit illis artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quo priùs perſuadent quàm doceant, vbi autem veritas docendo potiùs ſuadeat, quàm <pb facs="tcp:176510:5"/> ſuadendo doceat.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in 1. cap. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Declarabo cunctis iſtos ſe no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putare reos, qui honorem nominis Dei deferunt creaturae, &amp; relicto Domino, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruos adorant, ſibique perſuaſum habent Deum ſine mediatore inexorabilem eſſe, &amp; prorſus ignorant ad reges per tribunos &amp; comites eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum eſſe: quia homines vtique ſunt reges, &amp; neſciunt quibus debeant Re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicam credere. Ad Deum autem, quem nihil latet, omnium rerum merita nouit, ad promerendum ſuffragatore non eſt opus, ſed mente deuota. Vbicunque enim talis loquutus fuerit ei, procul dubio reſponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit illi.</hi> Sed aduerſarij noſtri, etſi videa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas ſacras ſuae ſententiae oppoſitas, confiteri tamen nolunt ſe in tetra erroris caligine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari. Quare haec Sancti Hilarij verba in illos haud indignè quadrare videntur:<note place="margin">Hilarius de Trinitate li. 6. cap.
84.</note> 
               <hi>Grauis &amp; periculoſus eſt lapſus in multis, etſi enim ſe intelligant, tamen pudor exurgendi autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſibi praeſumit, vt quod errant, prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam velint exiſtimari, quod cum multis er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, intelligentiam aſſerant veritatis.</hi> Et vnde illud quaeſo? Ex contemptu certè ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum, &amp; ex inſolenti ſuperbia qua inflati ſunt. Si circundarent ſibi quaſi murum firmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum, ſcripturaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctrinam, nunquam tàm citò ad illoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> interiora irrumpere poſſet hoſtis. <pb facs="tcp:176510:6"/> Tunc omnes errores, &amp; idola, &amp; ſimilitudines veritatis comminuerent atque diſpergerent, &amp; adeò iudicarent immunda, vt ea (menſtrua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae mulieris) ſordidiſſimo ſanguini co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pararent. Si corde non ficto diuinum auxilium compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larent, ſibi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nihil inaniter arrogarent, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ſupernè intrans in corda ſua, claro ſuo lumine mentes illoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illuſtraret, rationi (ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae formae) iubar ſuum infunderet, detegeret occulta, doctor<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fieret eorum quae ignorarent, tantum ſi illi ea quae ab illis ſunt, auferre vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. Sed omnia haec media, quibus poſſent ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uari, tanquam ſi nulli eſſent vſui, reſpuunt ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, qua de ratione illorum ſalus valde dé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperanda eſt. Concedat Deus <hi>Optimus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus</hi> vt reſipiſcant, &amp; veritatem agnoſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, dum huius lucis vſura, &amp; hoc vitae curriculo fruuntur, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> omnia figmenta, quae multis ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicibus aditum ad coelorum regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penitùs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercludunt, ſeponant, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> abijciant, &amp; Sancti Dauidis verborum recordatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obliuio nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deleat,<note place="margin">Pſal.
34.13, 14.</note> quae in Hebraico textu ſic ſe habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Iamim oheu chaiim hecaphets hais mi tou liroth vſephatheca, merag, leſconecha Netſor: Mirma Middabber. id eſt,</hi> Quis ille vir qui vult vitam, diliget dies ad videndum bonum, cuſtodi linguam tuam à malo, &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia tua à loquendo dolum. Et Beatus Paulus: <pb facs="tcp:176510:6"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, id eſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.20.</note>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>Empti eſtis pretio magno, glorificate igitur Deum in corpore veſtro, &amp; in ſpiritu veſtro, quae ſunt Dei.</hi> Temerè fortaſſis magis quàm prudenter hanc epiſtolam, nullis verborum phalaris floſculíſue Ciceronianis exaratam, tuae amplitudini di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care conabar, ſed meae temeritati tua igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcat humanitas, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> dignetur, vt ſub tuo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinio &amp; tutela, haec breuis recantationis meae declaratio in lucem aſpectum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> omnium intrepide prodeat, &amp; impioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maleuolentiam flocci pendat, quibus nocendi voluntas non deeſt, ſed officiendi poteſtas abest, &amp; declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta recumbit. Ne epiſtola haec longior ſit quàm par est, diutiùs tuam amplitudinem detinere nolo, ſed vt hoc meae erga te qualecunque ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruantiae monumentum beneuola manu ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere ne grauè tibi ducas, mirum in modum poſco &amp; imploro. Dominus Ieſus te tuoſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> (vir magnifice) muneribus ſuis ornet, augeat<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, &amp; in multos annos Eccleſiae ſuae conſeruet &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineat: Sereniſſimam verò <hi>Reginam Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betham,</hi> (quam exteri pleri<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> omnibus laudis ornamentis efferunt) protegat, &amp; longaeuam in terra faciat, ad gloriam Dei propaganda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ad comprimendam &amp; confringendam ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum
<pb facs="tcp:176510:7"/> ſuorum audaciam, denique ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolationem noſtram: Nobiliſſimòs Proceres, adeo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> omnes huius regni potentiſſimos ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes defendat, &amp; omni benedictionum genere cumulet, &amp; ad verae pietatis, &amp; regni Christi propagationem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tuae amplitudini addictiſsimus &amp; humilimus ſeruus Ioannes Nicholaus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:7"/>
            <head>The preface to the gentle <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD that is my recorde, and ſearcher of all mens heartes (good Chriſtian Reader) knovveth,<note place="margin">Ier. 11.20. &amp; 17.10. &amp;
20.12. 1. Chron. 28.9. 1. Sam. 16.7. Pſal. 7.10. Eſay. 29.13.</note> that with vnfeyned heart I greatly wiſhed this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of my repentance, &amp; deſire to be receiued to the true Church, to be imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for two principall cauſes: the one, to certifie my deare countrey men of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to the true Church, the other of my diſpoſition to do them good hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when it ſhal pleaſe God to increaſe me with greater knowledge, and to manifeſt how it hath pleaſed Chriſt our Sauiour the head ſhepheard,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.</note> to call me away by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments the faithfull and godly, from the whore of Babylon,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.9.</note> from the ſchole of error and from the temple of hereſie, to the City of righteouſneſſe, the true Church, his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled ſpouſe. I doubt not but that the godly and vnfeined louers of the glorious and comfortable Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt will heartily reioyce and giue God thanks, <pb facs="tcp:176510:8"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:176510:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:176510:9"/> that it was his diuine pleaſure to bring me a loſt ſheepe into his folde,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.12. Luk.
15.4.</note> &amp; to him make their prayers in my behalfe, that he of his bountifull mercie will vouchſafe to graunt me continuall perſeuerance therein euen vnto the ende of my life, that I may neuer ſwarue from his heauenly trueth vnto blindneſſe and errour,<note place="margin">Pſal.
125.5.</note> wherewith once ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by falſe prophets, I was holden cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. But nowe hauing the aſſiſtance of Gods holy Spirit, the trueth of his ſacred worde, and perfect loue of the faithfull on my ſide, I paſſe not what wicked Papiſtes ſpeake or do againſt me: their immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and vnciuill bitterneſſe proceeding from the furious and ſtormie paſſions of their poyſoned heartes I may well lament, but reſtraine I can not: therefore I ſay, Let the Papiſts here in England fret and fume, and ſay of my name what euill or ſlaunder they can deuiſe, let them write their letters to Rheims in Fraunce, and from thence to Rome with the poſte, and certifie all the Engliſh Scholers there, that the Popes ſcholer their owne companion and fellow ſtudent is reuolted from papiſtrie, hath left the Pope in plaine fielde, and quite deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, proteſted againſt his blaſphemies, <pb facs="tcp:176510:9"/> and renounced the deuiliſh dregges of all his Idolatrie. So ſoone as theſe letters ſhal come to viewe,<note place="margin">Robert Parſons ſometimes of Bailyol Colledge in Oxford.</note> they will name one Father <hi>Parſons</hi> Ieſuite a Prophet, or Southſayer, for that he at Rome in the Engliſh Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie in a certaine exhortation made to the ſchollers, prophecied that one or other of that company (my ſelfe being then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongeſt them) ſhoulde degenerate from their faith, and be the ouerthrowe of that colledge: he confirmed alſo the profe thereof by example, beginning with Chriſt and his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.16. Luk. 22.4. Ioh. 6.71.</note> &amp; pyking out Iudas one of the colledge of Chriſt that forſooke his maſter, and then from the colledge of the Apoſtles he named Nicholaus that reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.<note place="margin">Actes. 6.5. Apoc. 2.6.</note> Nowe will their diuines declayme in the refectory pulpit of my ſudden ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and eſtranging from their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly ſocietie. The triall and experience of their raſh iudgement, hatred, and enuie, mocking &amp; ſcoffing, had &amp; pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others, giueth me ſufficient notice that I ſhall incurre their like rayling, and miſreport. I knowe that I cannot be voyde of their imagined ſlaunders, in iudging me to be the firſt begotten ſonne of the deuil, I cannot eſcape their ſiniſter expoſition of <pb facs="tcp:176510:10"/> all things to the worſt: wherefore I muſt arme my ſelfe with patience, and ſeeing through Gods goodneſſe I am reduced from the miſerable captiuitie of blindneſſe and errour, to the true vnderſtanding and knowledge of Gods holy trueth, I neede take no great thought for their conceiued choller, ſlaunderous ſpeach, and rayling wordes of Sathans prompting, ſithens they haue dealt ſo maliciouſly with my betters. And as for their holy father the Popes curſe with booke, bell and candell, it ſhall not grieue me at all, neither will I take one vnquiet nappe for al his banning and curſing: and ſeeing I haue renounced his Popiſh church, wherein I neither heard the worde of God ſyncerely taught, the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, nor the Name of God duely called vpon: Seeyng that (I ſay) I forſooke the idolatrous church of Rome, and haue ſo gone from it,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.23. &amp; 3.26.</note> as Daniel went out of the lyons denne, and the three children out of the furnace, and am come to that Church, wherein the moſt earneſt Papiſtes them ſelues can not deny (if they will ſay truely and as they thinke in their owne conſcience) but all things be gouerned purely and reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb facs="tcp:176510:10"/> in this true Church of Chriſt, I haue a deſirous minde to profit my louing coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen, according to the Talent which God of his bountifulneſſe ſhall giue vnto me, in preaching vnto them his holy word, in exhorting them vnto watchfulneſſe and prayer againſt Romiſh doctrine, which is builded vpon falſe miracles and traditions of men, beeing the fantaſticall deuiſes of their buſie braine for lucre and ambition ſake: fynally in warning them vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of life, that both by their faith and conuerſation Gods name may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified. If thou art a member of that church the ſpouſe of Chriſt, whereof he is head, and not Antichriſt, the Biſhop of Rome, it needeth not then (good chriſtian Reader) much to entreat thee to take in good part this vnlearned declaration of my recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement made as it were ex tempore, my ſelfe being in priſon and wanting bookes, to the great impediment and hinderance of this my diſcourſe. The beneuolence of the Papiſtes I ſeeke not, for if I ſhoulde, it were but in vaine, I can not obteine it, for that I haue with vpright conſcience made a true rehearſall of ſuch thinges as I haue ſeene at Rome, yet not all, nor the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyeth <pb facs="tcp:176510:11"/> part thereof, but here one thing, and there another, and ſo fewe thinges in all: and this I adde in the ende, if they can not afforde one good worde by mee, yet for good fellowſhippe ſake let them then ſay, <hi>Requieſcat in pace,</hi> but let it be a ſolemne dirge for Ariſtotles ſoule, who neuer knew the true God, but euer liued in gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility &amp; blindnes of the trueth, that he may be deliuered out of Purgatory where they hold him to be, ſo that we may haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with him, &amp; know of him whether it be ſubſtantiall &amp; true diuinitie ſuch as he taught and ſet forth in writing, or els whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Plato his diuinitie, who was an Heathen or Gentile, and which of them is beſt: and as for the diuinitie which Chriſt preached, and was deliuered by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and receiued of the faithfull, they are not acquainted with. God euermore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame and direct me with his holy Spirit, that the zeale of his trueth may throughly pearce and poſſeſſe my heart, that I may ſafely walke in the wayes of righteouſnes &amp; holines al the dayes of my life, &amp; vtterly abandon &amp; deteſt all hypocriſie, &amp; idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſuperſtition.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:11"/>
            <head>A declaration of Gods benefites towardes me a wretched ſinner.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe prouident a patrone, and bountifull a father the Lorde of life hath bene vnto me his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankeful and rebellious childe, his ſundry and manifolde benefits doe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and this my vnfeyned reconciliation to the true Church doeth verefie the ſame, yea the continuance of his louing kindeneſſe was herein principally declared: for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as mine owne natural corruption wrought dayly in me the baniſhment out of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and the danger of reprobation, he not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in conſideration of my frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, neuer withſtoode to helpe me in all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers both bodily and ghoſtly, and to plucke me out of the pit of perdition, whereinto the haynouſneſſe of my offences haled me by violence. Oh gratious God, howe ſhall I a ſinner, conceiued in ſinne, and brought vp in iniquitie, worthily aduance the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of thy loue? who ſhal giue me a heart to conceiue this thy kindneſſe? whence ſhal I haue vtterance to ſound out thy mercie? <pb facs="tcp:176510:12"/> Of my ſelf (becauſe I am a veſſell of wrath ſubiect to ſinne, death, hel &amp; condemnation) I can not conceiue ſo perfect a worke: thou therefore which art the euerlaſting foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.13. Iam. 1.17.</note> giue it me, oh giue it me, and I ſhall haue it, and in the hauing of it I ſhall magnifie thy Name, extoll thy power, &amp; marueile at thy mercy. Thou haſt had ſpeciall regard to my fraile eſtate, and ſafetie of my ſoule. I had once loſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pearle of thy bleſſed Goſpell,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.45, 46.</note> which is the true iewel of all chriſtian ioy, but by thy gratious gift I haue found it againe, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof, Chriſtian duety bindeth me to take the ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.12, 13.</note> and burne the ſame vpon the altar of an humble heart, that the redolent &amp; perfumed incenſe thereof aſcending vp into heauen,<note place="margin">Pſal.
51.17.</note> may be acceptable to thy diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, whoſe ſpeciall delight is in ſuch a burnt ſacrifice and oblation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="conversion" type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A diſcouerie or laying open</hi> of my zeale in Poperie, and howe I preached before that Antichriſt of Rome, and alſo of the cauſes of my moſt happie conuerſion to the trueth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not yet a twelue-moneth paſt (good Chriſtian audience, &amp; welbeloued brethren in our ſauiour Chriſt) ſince that, before ſome of you nowe pryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſcholefelowes, I preached, as you knowe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by our ſuperiours at Rome, in defence of the Romiſhe Religion, which nowe (God be thanked therefore) (being redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the godly and dayly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the ryght worſhipfull Syr Owyn Hopton Knight, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of her Highneſſe Towre of London, the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; pith thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions <pb facs="tcp:176510:13"/> of learned Preachers, which through his meanes and permiſſion, had acceſſe vnto me, and the hearing of their fruiteful ſermons, confirmed by the true and liuely word of Chriſt Ieſus) I vtterly deteſt. How earneſt I was then in perſwading the Engliſh Students to embrace Papiſtrie, and in exhorting you ſometimes my Scholefellowes, (as the Popes Apoſtles,) fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to doe your meſſage, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to take the croſſe of Chriſt vpon you in all troubles and afflictions, and couragiouſly to abide Martyrdome, I thinke you haue in remembrance. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout halfe a yeere paſt,<note place="margin">Anno. 1580.</note> I was alſo requeſted by the Prefect or Maſter of the Engliſh Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, named father
<hi>Peter</hi> Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite, a Spaniarde borne, to make a Sermon in the Latin tongue, vpon the feſtiual day of Peter <hi>ad <pb facs="tcp:176510:13"/> Vincula,</hi> certayne Engliſh Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the citie, and ſome of the Popes Chappel, with other ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers being preſent at dinner. I preached then contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Religion, againſt faith, the buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of our defence, the Towre of refuge, the enemie of deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the comfortreſſe of the afflicted, and the perfecte way to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I preached alſo repugnantly to maintaine popiſh idolatrie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the heauenly Goſpell, the newe Teſtament, and laſt wil of our Sauiour Chriſt. Thus dyd I wilfully fyght agaynſt Gods worde, albeit my conſcience cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within me day &amp; night, This is not the right way to get eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, thou muſt worſhip God,<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.9.</note> and not a ſtocke or ſtone. Well, it pleaſed God of his mercifull goodneſſe to viſite me with grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſickneſſe both of bodie and minde, two dayes after I made <pb facs="tcp:176510:14"/> this Latin Sermon, which was the Wedneſday after S. Peter <hi>ad Vincula</hi> his day.<note place="margin">Auguſt. 5.</note> Truely then lying very ſicke in my bedde, and more like to die, then liue, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſo pricked and diſquieted me, that I feared condemnation: my conſcience alwayes ſuggeſting, and as it were telling me, Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie to bee an idolatrous and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious religion. Yet for all that, I thought that religion to haue bene beſt, although I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted often againſt the ſame, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that many of my ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felowes ſuſpected me to haue bin an heretike (for ſo terme they Proteſtantes.<note place="margin">Act.
24.14.</note>) One of you that was prefecte of our chamber in the Engliſhe Seminarie, may eaſely gather that I was no true louer of the Goſpel, when as I ſo ſharply ſpake, and preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the profeſſors therof. And how vnwiſely I ſlept, in the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt <pb facs="tcp:176510:14"/> time of the yere the laſt win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vpon hard boards, forſaking my bedde,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.28. Luk. 18.12.</note> howe I ſcourged my ſelfe with whipcordes, and how I faſted twiſe in the weeke: you may coniecture by this, that I was a Papiſt, which woulde ſeeke ſo to ſhorten mine owne life: you knowe alſo, how I tooke thereby a vehement cough with continuall ſpitting, which ſince your departure grewe to a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſeaſe, wherof I thanke God I am nowe recouered. My Confeſſor dyd aduiſe me to ſuch and ſo extreme diſcipline and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of my bodie, as had I ſtil followed his directions, I had bene dead yer nowe, and put in the grotte, for graues haue they none at Rome, but Vawtes. If this be good or wholſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel for a man ſo to correct himſelf, that hee ſhall bee the cauſe of his owne death, iudge you. But I <pb facs="tcp:176510:15"/> left thoſe ſuperſtitions, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered reaſon to rule my wil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was too late, and hauing recouered my health, I preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe before the Pope, and obteyned leaue to goe to <hi>Rheims,</hi> for that the ayre there was more te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate. I had before that time made an Oration &amp; a Sermon in the Latin tongue, preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pope and foure Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and before all them that were with the Pope in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorie. If you my brethren yet priſoners within the Towre, deny the aſſertion thereof, yet to your ſhame, and my credit, they that ſhall goe to Rome for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſake, may ſafely goe to the Popes Protonotary, dwelling faſt by Saint Peters church in the inquiſitory palace, or to any of his clarkes, and there make inquiſition of my name, which is regiſtred in three great paper
<pb facs="tcp:176510:15"/> volumes, of ſuch as are alwaies preſent, wryting in chambers, to whom all men without daunger may reſorte: where, turning to my name, they ſhall finde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Oration conteyning tenne ſheetes in Paper, for the which the Pope gaue me great thankes, and ſo did the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, with all the reſt. Moreouer (which I had almoſt forgotten) being before the Pope, I had a wallet for foure Prieſtes, and a Doctor, &amp; others, full of Agnus deis, Grana benedicta, Medel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, Croſſes, and Beades, with other traſſhes: and foraſmuch as I had neuer before that tyme ſeene the Pope bleſſing wallets, I did hold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wallet before him, and would haue had him to hold it vpon his lappe, and ſo to haue bleſt it with his red cappe. Well, I neuer drewe backe my hand from him, vntill extraordinarily <pb facs="tcp:176510:16"/> he had bleſt it three times, which before that time as I thinke, was neuer ſeene. So that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is happie, which hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuch a wallet, with ſo many bleſſings, wherby (perhaps) they may deliuer their Grandſiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace out of purgatory: it is a ſtrange thing to ſee what vertue may be thruſt into a wallet. O vnwiſe people that truſt to ſuch traſſhes. If I had money plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I would get you a thouſand bleſſings, but God bleſſe vs all from ſuch hypocriticall benedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Well, concerning my iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I forſooke Fraunce, &amp; came not at Rheins: but traueiled tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Germany, and arryued in Englande, and was within eight dayes taken priſoner, and brought to the Towre: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there kept in priſon for Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, I thought it good to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the eſtate of my religion, not fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <pb facs="tcp:176510:16"/> the death of the bodie,<note place="margin">Matt. 10 28. Luk. 12.5.</note> ſo much as the condemnation of my ſoule, to burne in hell fire for euer, if I helde not true religion, although that others in their bookes ſhould write me a holy Martyr. Thus in priſon with a ſorowfull minde, a carefull thought, and a troubleſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I ſpent the time, where with ſobbing teares and hearty prayers, I craued of GOD, that he of his merciful goodnes, would vouchſafe to aſſiſt mee in al troubles and perſecution, that valiantly I might bee able to fight vnder his banner, ſtoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ouercome the ſubtil aſſaults of the deuill,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.38. &amp; 16 24. Actes.
5.41. 1. Pet. 3.14, 15. 2. Tim. 2 11, 12.</note> prudently to deſpiſe the deceitful promiſes of worldly felicitie, manfully to abandon the frailtie of the fleſh, and ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take vp the croſſe, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe Chriſte, euen to the death, the death of martyrdome. It <pb facs="tcp:176510:17"/> pleaſed God, hearing this my fooliſh petition, &amp; knowing me to be ſeduced by falſe prophets, (I ſay not, ne dare ſay, ſuch as you my brethren are,) for that I hope you haue determined to recant your wicked religion: but I doe, and may boldly ſay, ſuch as you were before your apprehenſion, and impryſonment here in the Towre. Well, I ſay, it pleaſed God of his goodnes, knowing me to bee in errour, to lighten myne eies, that I might clearely ſee the abominable Idolatrie, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious ſuperſtition and vaine ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, which are vſed &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in al Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, where Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt reigneth, who is an enemy of God, a robber of his honour, a falſe ſeducer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, a diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weales, a corrupter of Gods holy word, a Coziner of princes, a ſetter downe of newe lawes &amp; ſtrange co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, <pb facs="tcp:176510:17"/> otherwiſe then our maſter Chriſt in his bleſſed word doeth allowe: &amp; briefly, a great ſtumbling blocke of offence to infinite thouſandes of the true louers of the Goſpell, an open perſecutour, &amp; a bloudie butcher. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my heart was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to perceiue the fickle fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this vnſauored religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I recanted from the bottome of my heart, and bewailed that euer I was a Papiſt: but afterwards ſomewhat comforting my ſelfe, I craued, and doe craue, and ſhall with Gods helpe aſke mercy and forgiueneſſe, for al my idolatrous crymes and faultes committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his diuine maieſtie. I ſhal become of a Rebell a true ſubiect, of an enemie of the trueth, an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracer thereof. I will ſtudy and endeuor by God his grace during my life, that his wrath and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation worthily deſerued, may be pacified, &amp; that I may be founde <pb facs="tcp:176510:18"/> acceptable in his ſight at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of iudgement,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.16. Apo. 20.12.</note> when eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhall giue an accompt of his Stewardſhip. I wil moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer do what I can to reforme the iudgement and conſcience of our Aduerſaries, and to bring the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Goſpell to the loue thereof.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.16, 18.</note> But it is not in him that willeth, neither in him that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but in God that ſheweth mercie. There ſhall want no dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in me by gods helpe, in this my firſt ſermon after my recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to haue you my brethren brought into the way of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who yet hitherto (as it ſeemeth) either ignorantly or wilfully wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der from the ſame. I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen a Theame fit for my purpoſe to diſcouer the errours and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of your religion. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I enterpriſe to diſcourſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my text, I thinke it moſt needeful to make my prayer to God, that
<pb facs="tcp:176510:18"/> I the preacher may with a pure minde, feruent zeale, wholeſome doctrine and bolde vtterance, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you that bee here preſent, and that you the hearers may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently marke, &amp; obediently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is taught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you may heare Gods word with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; practiſe the ſame in your life &amp; conuerſation, that I may preach to the honor of God, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> extolling of his benefits towards vs miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wretches, to the edifying of his church, to the enlargement of his holy kingdom, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the trueth of his ſacred Goſpel, to the extirpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne, to the aboliſhing of Papiſtry, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reformation of you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bee infected therewith, to the plucking down of Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; finally to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> building vp of the walles of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In which prayer I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende to your good deuotion the whole eſtate of Chriſt his church milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here on earth, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recantation">
            <pb facs="tcp:176510:19"/>
            <head>The recantation of Iohn Nichols a Seminarie man, &amp; lately
<hi>the Popes Scholer, made in the Tower of</hi> London, the fifth day of February, 1581. &amp; the 23. yere of her Maieſties moſt bleſsed reigne, before Syr Owyn Hopton, Knight, with diuers other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Citizens of London, and many others. Where alſo were preſent certaine of the ſame ſect, and lately his fellowes and companions.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Matth. 7.15.</bibl>
                  <p>Cauete a falſis prophetis, qui veniunt ad vos induti veſtibus ouium, ſed intus lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi ſunt rapaces.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beware of falſe prophetes, which come to you in ſheepes clothing, but inwardly they are rauening wolues.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this parcell of ſcripture, good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian audience, and welbeloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we haue three things worthie to be noted. The firſt is a caueat, warning, or watch word giuen by our Maſter Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:176510:19"/> he ſayth, <hi>Cauete a falſis prophetis?</hi> Beware of falſe prophets. Falſe teachers of mens traditions, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Prieſtes, craftie ſeducers, he biddeth vs take heede of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Iuglers. In the ſeconde poynt or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma, he telleth vs their outward habit, by the which we may diſtinguiſh and know them from true Prophets, when as he ſaith,
<hi>Qui veniunt ad vos induti ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus ouium:</hi> Which come to you in ſheepes clothing. In the thirde poynt, which is the ſhutting vp of the ſentence, he ſheweth vs their inward habit, <hi>Sed intrinſecus ſunt Lupi rapaces:</hi> But inwardly they are rauening wolues, deuourers of the flocke. Theſe three poyntes or diuiſions will I handle, God willing, in order, as the text gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me occaſion. Our auncient aduerſary the ſerpent (derely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our ſauiour Chriſt) was neuer more buſie to ſeeke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction <pb facs="tcp:176510:20"/> both of body and ſoule, the time neuer more dangerous to fall, the people neuer ſo leude &amp; prone to ſinne and idolatrie, the Papiſtes neuer ſo vigilant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their owne countrymen, as in theſe our latter dayes, whereof Chriſt prophecied: neyther ſeeke they onely to ſpoyle them of their goods, but alſo to plucke them from the trueth and ready waye to ſaluation, vnto wicked errour and idolatrous ſuperſtition, and from the perfect path that leadeth to life euerlaſting, vnto the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table way of endeleſſe torment &amp; vtter deſtruction. Wherefore my brethren, if you haue the feare of God before your eyes, if you haue the loue of trueth dwelling in you, if you haue an eſpeciall care to ſaue your ſoules, yeelde not to the ſerpentes perſwaſion, take heede of falſe prophets, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent not to the doctrine of Romiſh prieſts, <pb facs="tcp:176510:20"/> the Popes Apoſtles: For ſayeth one,
<hi>Dum Romani ſacerdotes qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maxime poſſunt, enituntur multa praedicare, quae ſaluti animarum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenire videantur, non pauca praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, quae ad perennem animarum perniciem ducu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> Whiles that the Romiſh prieſts endeuor as much as they may, to preache many thinges, which ſeeme to agree to the ſaluation of ſoules, then teach they not few things which tende to the perpetuall deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The firſt point of their deuiliſh doctrine, in ſeducing the blinde and ignorant people, is this, To tell vs, that we leaue this article of our Creede vnbeleeued, <hi>Credo ſanctam Catholicam Eccleſiam,</hi> I beleeue in the holy Catholike Church, if we acknowledge not the Romane church to be the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly catholique Church. As though that were true. In the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all the learned and godly, the
<pb facs="tcp:176510:21"/> Catholique Church is diſperſed ouer the face of the earth, not tied or vnited to any proper place as Rome, or perſon as the Pope. The Councill of Nice, in tyme paſt committed the charge of the Catholique Church, to three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Patriarkes, Rome, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, and Antioch, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards came to Conſtantinople. Nilius in his booke <hi>de primatu Romani Pontificis,</hi> of the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of the Biſhop of Rome, ſayth,
<hi>Quandoquidem quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciae ſpectant ad eccleſiam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam, aliquae ad Epiſcopum Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xandriae, &amp; aliquae ad Epiſcopum Conſtantinapolaeos, iam non magis ſubditae ſunt Romano Epiſcopo, quam Romanus Epiſcopus ſubditus ſit illis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Foraſmuch as certayne countries are limited to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Rome, certeine to the Biſhop of Alexandria, and certeine to the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, they <pb facs="tcp:176510:21"/> are now no more vnder him, then he vnder them. I gather by this Councill of Nice, which all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of Rome do allowe, that the Church of Rome was not onely accompted Catholique, but alſo the Church of Alexandria was taken to be Catholique, &amp; in like maner the Church of Antioch. I am certeine you wil not deny the Biſhop of Rome euer heretofore to haue bene, &amp; as yet to be Pope, therefore I inferre the Biſhop of Alexandria, and the Biſhoppe of Antioch to be Popes, &amp; Chriſtes Vicars, and ſo conſequently to be three Popes, and three Chriſtes Vicars. Haue you taught our Engliſh men ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be three Popes, &amp; three Catholique chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and are you put in priſon therefore? No, no, I know it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. I take you to be hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. Pope Gregory the xiii.<note place="margin">Greg. 13.</note> of that name, or rather by his right <pb facs="tcp:176510:22"/> name, <hi>Hugo Bon compaignion,</hi> Hugh goodfellowe, hath brybed you with his money, that you ſhould preach him to be Pope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and none other. Is this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtuffe, <hi>vt amor nummi eſſet ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus multorum,</hi> that the loue of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſhould be the fall of many? I will ſpeake a litle more touching your Catholique church. <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Roma eſt metropolis Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae ditio nis,</hi> Rome is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther church (not of the whole worlde) but of the prouince of Rome. I wil not ſpeake of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Ireland, Scotland, Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marke, <hi>Polonia, Suetia, Bohoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> of Germanie, <hi>Heluetia, Pruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Ruſſia, Lituania, Pomerania, Auſtria, Rhetia, Vallis, Tellina, &amp;c.</hi> where the Goſpel floriſheth. But is your church y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother church? and hath your Pope gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and iuriſdiction ouer the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in Aſia and Affricke? It is
<pb facs="tcp:176510:22"/> well knowen that there is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie in Aſia, Affricke, Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Aethiopia, Cyprus, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople and other places, where the Pope dareth not once peepe, for all his pontificalitie at Rome. And in reſpect of all Chriſtian aſſemblies &amp; faithfull members, whereſoeuer the church is called Catholique, that is meant vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall. So that your church and all churches are to bee tried and knowen not by your erring coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, canons, conſtitutions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and gloſſes, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, which is the touchſtone of trueth. Ireneus ſaith,<note place="margin">Lib. 3. cap. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na &amp; firmamentum eccleſiae eſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelium &amp; ſpiritus vitae.</hi> The pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and buttreſſe of the church is the Goſpell and ſpirit of life.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de vnitate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. lib. 3. cap. 3.</note> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Donatiſtes ſaith, <hi>Sunt certe libri dominici quorum authoritati vtrique conſentimus, vtrique credimus, vtrique ſeruimus: <pb facs="tcp:176510:23"/> ibi quaeramus eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ibi diſcutia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cauſam noſtram:</hi> There are verely bookes of our Lorde, vnto the authoritie whereof eche part agreeth, eche part beleeueth, and eche part regardeth,<note place="margin">Church to be ſought in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> there let vs ſeeke for the church, and thereby let vs examine and trie our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. This I thought good to note here, leaſt that any of this faithfull congregation ſhould at any time be caried away with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bare name of your catholique churche. Nowe moreouer you ſeeke to proue your church by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, multitude, ſucceſſion of perſon or place, none otherwiſe then falſe coyners, who will not haue their money knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the fineneſſe of golde, or by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, but by the waight, by the ſounde, by the coyne, and by the colour which they may eaſely counterfeite. Therefore they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge antiquitie vnto vs, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb facs="tcp:176510:23"/> that which was ſpoken vnto Iob by one of his friendes,<note place="margin">Iob. cap.
8.8.</note> 
               <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſule quaeſo priſcam aetatem, et com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>para te ad perueſtigationem maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum illorum:</hi> Aſke for the auncient generation, and prepare thy ſelfe to ſeeke for the fathers.<note place="margin">Iob.
32.7</note> 
               <hi>Prouecti aetate loquentur, et annoſi notam facient ſapientiam:</hi> Dayes ſhall ſpeake, &amp; the multitude of yeeres ſhall teach wiſedome. To whom I could anſwere by Iob himſelf, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verſe next following,<note place="margin">9. verſ.</note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtri ſemper ſapientes non ſunt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſenes omni tempore intelligunt Iudicium.</hi> The maſters are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies wiſe, neither do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde men alwayes vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Iudgement. <hi>Profectò ſpiritus ille in mortali,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8. verſ.</note> 
               <hi>et afflatus omni potentis efficit eos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligentes:</hi> It is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God, &amp; not yeres, that ought to ſpeak in man.<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Pet. Diac. cap.
34.</note> If antiquitie ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, why then (I pray you) is the Church compared to a litle <pb facs="tcp:176510:24"/> Barke or Ship, which the more ſhe is vpon the ſea, the more ſhee leaketh: vnto a houſe, which with age decayeth &amp; falleth to ruine: to a Citie and the policie of it, which is corrupted from tyme to time, if it be not brought backe to the firſt inſtitution: &amp; to a mans body, whereunto yeeres do bryng all kindes of euill: to be ſhort, age is euen as ſickeneſſe it ſelfe to the moſt healthfull and temperate body in the world. I ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that antiquitie alone ought to make vs thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the Church there is a great ſicknes, and much fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes, &amp; that euen for this cauſe alone, without any longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation, it is requiſite to bring a broome to purge it, and to call for a Phyſition. So farre is it off, that for theſe things a man ſhould mainteyne your Churche to bee pure &amp; holy, as you do. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more I demand, how you wil an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere <pb facs="tcp:176510:24"/> vnto Saint Auguſtine, entreating vpon the threeſcore and fourth Pſalme, who ſayth, That Ieruſalem began by Abel, and Babylon by Cain. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made by Iſaac, and the baſtardiſe by Iſmael. Who were the elders? If antiquitie were a marke of the trueth, how woulde you haue anſwered vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, who tolde Chriſt that they were the children of Abraham,<note place="margin">Iohn 8.33.</note> who was the firſt father of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers? They had their Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie from the creation of the fyrſt man, they did alledge the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants that were made betweene God &amp; them. Notwithſtanding, Chriſte being ſent vnto them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe promiſes, vnder the ſhadowe of this antiquitie, they maliciouſly called hym the carpenters ſonne, a Samaritane,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.55. Iohn 8.48. Marke 1.27.</note> one that had the deuil, &amp; a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Noueltie. And there is <pb facs="tcp:176510:25"/> great likelyhood, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if ſome of you Papiſts had bene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there, ſeeing at that time they vſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame arguments, you would haue hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to haue crucified him. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, what wil you anſwere vnto the Greeke Churches, the Armenians, Ethiopia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp;c. foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtles, and as olde as the church of Rome, yea and elder too, ſeeing that the Church of Chriſt, as we knowe, tooke her beginning from the Eaſt to the Weſt? If antiquitie be a marke of holines and puritie, they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and pure: and if they bee holy and pure, then the latin Church in compariſon of them, is moſte vnholy and impure. If they bee Heretiques and impure, then it followeth that antiquitie is not a marke to proue the holines or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Church. Howe then? ſhall we reiect antiquitie? nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we imbrace it with all our <pb facs="tcp:176510:25"/> hearts, ſo that it bee agreeable to Gods worde. Tertullian
<hi>de Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginibus velandis,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do initium ab aliqua ignorantia vel ſimplicitate ſortita, in vſum per ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſionem corroboratur, &amp; ita ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus veritatem vendicatur. Sed Dominus noſter Chriſtus veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe, non conſuetudinem cognomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauit. Viderint ergò, quibus nouum eſt, quod ſibi vetus eſt. Haereſes non tam nouitas, quàm veritas reuincit. Quodcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que aduerſus veritatem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, hoc erit haereſis, etiam vetus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo:</hi> Cuſtome either of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, or of ignorance, getting once an entrie, is inured &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by ſucceſſion, and then is defended againſt the trueth. But Chriſt our Lorde calleth himſelfe trueth, and not cuſtome.<note place="margin">Ioh.
14.6.</note> Let them take heede therefore, vnto whome the thing ſeemeth newe, that in it ſelfe is olde. It is not ſo much the noueltie of the
<pb facs="tcp:176510:26"/> matter, as the trueth that repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth an hereſy. Whatſoeuer ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth againſt the trueth, is an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, be the cuſtome thereof ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo olde. <hi>Victi ratione opponunt conſuetudinem, quaſi conſuetudo ſit maior veritate.</hi> Beyng ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with reaſon, they defende themſelues with cuſtome, as though cuſtome were better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trueth. We may not preſcribe of cuſtome, but wee muſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Cuſtome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trueth is the mother of error. <hi>Iſtud non eſt curandum quod ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ante noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tempus fecit, ſed id precipue nobis curae debet eſſe, ꝙ a Chriſto factum eſt. Non eſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda nobis hominum conſuetudo, ſed dei veritas expectanda:</hi> That is, We muſt not regard y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which any other hath done before vs, but we muſt regarde that which Chriſt hath done, which is before all. For we muſt not followe the <pb facs="tcp:176510:26"/> cuſtome of men, but the trueth of God. Againe he ſaith,<note place="margin">De ſeipſo ad Pompeian. epiſt. 9.</note>
               <hi>Mos ſine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, eſt vetuſtas erroris. Et dixit dominus, Ego ſum veritas: &amp; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutus eſt Dominus, Ego ſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo:</hi> Cuſtome without trueth is an old error. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath ſaid, I am the trueth, and not, I am cuſtome. Ignatius ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ignatius ad Philadelph. Canon. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetud. diſt. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Quem non audire eſt manifeſta perditio:</hi> Whome not to heare is manifeſt perdition. See then howe the moſt auncient ſende vs alwayes to learne the trueth of him, which is moſt ancient of all. Thus much briefely touching antiquitie or cuſtome. Nowe let vs come to multitude. It is ſayde expreſſely,<note place="margin">Exod. 23.2,</note> 
               <hi>Exodus.</hi> 23. <hi>Ne inſiſtito veſtigiis potentiorum ad mala:</hi> Thou ſhalt not folowe a multitude to do euil. Alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>Lata eſt porta, &amp; ſpatioſa via quae ducit in exitium, multique ſunt qui ambula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t per mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius.</hi> Wide is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:176510:27"/> gate, and broade is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which go in thereat. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.
<hi>Ne time, ô par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue grex, nam viſum eſt patri meo dare vobis regnum:</hi> Feare not, my litle flocke, for it is my fathers will to giue you a kingdome. Moreouer, wee ſee how that all the worlde was brought to one Noah, and afterwardes came to Abraham, then God choſe one people of Iſrael, the leaſt (as it is ſayd) of all peoples, and finally of all peoples the leaſt parte, that is to wit, Chriſtendome: which for this cauſe he calleth a litle flocke, ſo farre forth, that S. Auguſtine ſaith, That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in one Abel, &amp; in one Enoch. <hi>Auguſt. ſuper Pſalm.</hi> 128. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore multitude ought rather to be preſumption, then a marke of the true Church. Foraſmuch alſo as man by nature is alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:176510:27"/> more prone to euill, then to any goodnes, if multitude ſhoulde take place, then Paynims ſhould be happier then we be, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſurpaſſe in nomber. For whereas there is one that beleeueth in Chriſt our Sauiour, you haue a thouſande that beleeue him not. What a multitude is there of Turkes, of Iewes, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels? Alſo in Noah his tyme, what a multitude there was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would not acknowledge God, nor folow his commandements, nor giue credit to Noah his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but with one conſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt him, mocked him, &amp; his religion, <hi>Gen. chap.</hi> 6. The Samaritanes were more in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, then they of the tribe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. And in Iuda and Iſrael, the multitude of the idolaters was the greater. For the Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias made his complaint, that he was left alone, &amp; that all the reſt
<pb facs="tcp:176510:28"/> had forſaken their liuing Lorde, and giuen them ſelues to idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: and as you may reade in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> 4.<note place="margin">1. King. 22.6, 13, 24.</note> There aroſe vp 400. falſe Prophets, who ſwarued from Gods lawe, and folowed their owne imaginations, againſt one good Prophet Micheas. And the Prophets crie,<note place="margin">Ierem.
18.18</note> 
               <hi>Omnem popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſeductum fuiſſe, a regibus vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad Sacerdotes &amp; Prophetas:</hi> That all the people were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, euen from the Kings, to the Prieſtes and Prophets. In the Church of Chriſt alſo, nomber &amp; multitude ſhall haue as ſmall roume: for euen at the beginning thereof,<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.1. Ioh. 12.38. Rom. 10.16.</note> it was ſayde, Who hath beleeued our word? and to whom hath the Arme of the Lorde bene reueiled? Anon after the death of our Sauiour, the Scholemen hold, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for one inſtant, the church ſtood in the Virgin Mary alone. In the time of Arrius, almoſt the <pb facs="tcp:176510:28"/> world throughout, was of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian hereſie, and fewe beſides A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius, with fiue of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, profeſſed the true fayth.<note place="margin">Theod. lib. 2. cap. 16.</note> Wherefore the Emperour of the Arrians ſayd, That foure or fiue perſons with their Athanaſius, woulde trouble the peace of the world. To whom Liberius the Biſhop of Rome anſwered, That his ſolitude or fewneſſe did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit diminiſh the worde of faith. As for the declining eſtate of the Church, wee are giuen to wit, That when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of man ſhall come, before whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming Antichriſt ſhall ſeduce the world, <hi>Neque fides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 24.12, 37.</note> 
               <hi>neque charitas inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta erit in terra, &amp; iſti dies erunt tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dies Noah &amp; Lot:</hi> There ſhall neither faith nor charity be found on the earth, and thoſe dayes ſhal be as the daies of Noah &amp; Lot, &amp;c. The Eclipſe then of this Moone ſhalbe as it were vniuerſal, al the <pb facs="tcp:176510:29"/> whole earth being put betweene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church &amp; the ſunne. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we ſhall finde no other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in ſuch darknes, then the multitude, we ſhall haue no part with that litle nomber. So much for multitude, whereof the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts make great account. Nowe will I ſpeake a litle of Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which you, my brethren, take to bee a very ſubſtantiall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the trueth. But Chriſt ſaith in the 23. of Matthewe, <hi>In cathedra Moſis ſedent Scribae &amp; Phariſaei:</hi> By order of Succeſſion, the Scribes and Phariſes ſit in Moſes chaire. Annas and Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas touching Succeſſion, were aſwel Biſhops as Aaron and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leazar. Of Succeſſion S. Paul ſaith to the faithfull at Epheſus, <hi>Scio quod poſt diſceſſum meum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabunt lupi rapaces, ex vobis ipſis exurgent viri peruerſa loquentes:</hi> I knowe that after my departure <pb facs="tcp:176510:29"/> hence, rauening wolues ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſucceede mee, and out of yourſelues there ſhall (by Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion) ſpring vp men ſpeaking peruerſly. Therfore S. Hierome ſaith, <hi>Non ſanctorum filii ſunt, qui tenent loca ſanctorum:</hi> They bee not alwayes the children of holy men, that (by ſucceſſion) haue the places of holy men. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Pope himſelfe will ſay, as it is before alledged, <hi>In Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſi deſint bona acquiſita per meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſufficiunt quae a loci praedeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore praeſtantur:</hi> If the Pope want good things by his own merits, the good thinges which hee hath (by Succeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) of Peter his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor, are ſufficient. And the gloſe vpon <hi>Petrus fecit Papas hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redes bonitatis ſuae:</hi> Peter made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes, heires of his goodnes by Succeſſion. And againe, <hi>Papa recipit a cathedra ſanctitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The Pope receiueth his holines by <pb facs="tcp:176510:30"/> ſucceſſion of his chaire. Such affiance ſometime had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scribes and Phariſes in their ſucceſſion: therefore they ſayde,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.33, 53.</note> We are the children of Abraham. Vnto vs hath God made his promiſes: art thou greater then our father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham?<note place="margin">Iohn 9.29.</note> As for Chriſt, we know not from whence hee came, or what can he ſhewe for his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? And when our Sauiour went about to reforme the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and errors, they ſayde vnto him,<note place="margin">Matt. 21.23. Iohn 2.18.</note> By what power doeſt thou theſe things? and who gaue thee this authoritie? where is thy ſucceſſion? Vpon which wordes Beda ſaith,<note place="margin">Beda in Matth. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Intelligi volunt diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li eſſe quod fecit:</hi> They woulde haue the people vnderſtand (for that he had no ſolemne ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that al that he did was of the deuill.<note place="margin">Cyrillus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena in Luc. 39.</note> And Cyrillus frameth their words in this ſort, <hi>Tu ortus ex Iuda, commiſſos nobis faſces v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpas:</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:176510:30"/> Thou beeing of the tribe of Iuda, (and therefore hauing no right vnto the prieſthoode) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt vpon thee the office that is committed vnto vs. Likewiſe Chryſoſtom imagineth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes thus to ſay,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Mat. Hom. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Tu de ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali familia natus non es, Senatus tibi hoc non conceſſit, Caeſar non donauit:</hi> Thou art not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of prieſts, the Councill hath not graunted it thee, the Emperour hath not giuen it thee. Thus to mainteine themſelues in credit, (for that they had ſucceſſion, and continuance from Aaron, and ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire) they kept Chriſt quite out of poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">Matt. 23.2.</note> and ſayd vnto him then, euen as you my brethren ſaye nowe vnto vs, Who euer taught vs this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious doctrine before? what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſucceſſion of perſons, and vocation haue we? what Biſhop admitted vs? who confirmed vs?
<pb facs="tcp:176510:31"/> who allowed vs? Therefore (good chriſtian hearers) let not theſe the Papiſtes great wordes much abaſh vs. The Scribes &amp; Phariſes in the like caſes vſed the like language long ago. But let me aſke you a queſtion. Howe can you ſhewe any demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or probabilitie, that the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your church is lawfull? If there were any church that could alledge ſucceſſion of perſons, it were the church of the Iewes, for they were of the houſe of Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, from the father to the ſonne, and beſides them none might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Moreouer to them it was promiſed, that they ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo for euer. And in deed, when the Prophets exhorted them to reformation, they had no other thing in their mouth, but this, <hi>Lex a Sacerdote non peribit, neque conſilium a ſapiente, neque ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum a propheta:</hi> The lawe ſhall <pb facs="tcp:176510:31"/> not periſh from the prieſt; nor the counſell from the wiſe, nor the word from the Prophet. But the ſpirit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde anſwered them, <hi>Quomodo dicitis, Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſumus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; lex Iehouae penes nos eſt? vtique ecce ad falſitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> operatur ſtylus, ad falſitatem operantur legis periti: fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerúntne ſapientes vt erubeſcerent? conſternatíne ſunt &amp; capti? ecce verbum Iehouae ſpernunt, eccuius rei ſapientia ineſſet eis?</hi> Howe ſay ye, We are wiſe, and the lawe of the Lord is with vs? For it is in vaine, that the pen is made, and that there is a ſcribe: wiſe men are confounded, and ſeeing that they haue reiected the worde of the Lord, what ſhalbe their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome any more? In like maner when the Iewes boaſted to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that they were of the ſeede of Abraham,<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> I know it wel (ſaith he) but the deuil is your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And in very deede this ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue <pb facs="tcp:176510:32"/> and hereditarie wiſdome crucified Chriſt, and reiected ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation offred vnto them, as alſo this ſelf ſame ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (although it be only pretended) worſhippeth Antichriſt, and interteyneth her owne perdition. Moreouer I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande what theſe alledgers of ſucceſſion would haue anſwered to the <hi>Arrians, Samoſetans, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, &amp;c.</hi> who had their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning continued from the firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops euen to themſelues, and namely to <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and
<hi>Samoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus,</hi> both which were lawfully called to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patriarchal churches, the one to Conſtantinople, and the other to Antioch? Alſo, what will you anſwere to the ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alledged by al the Greeke and eaſt churches? To be ſhort, to the reformed churches of England, De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mark, Swethe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a great part of Almaigne, through all which there is at this daye this ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <pb facs="tcp:176510:32"/> from Biſhop to biſhop, from Paſtor to Paſtor? If you wil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Popes ſucceſſion, wee deny it you, &amp; it is another que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. If ſimply ſucceſſion, you haue loſt your cauſe. If your doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, then we gaine this poynt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſimple ſucceſſion of perſons without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſucceſſion of doctrine, is nothing worth. With this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Pope Adrian the fourth, I end to diſcourſe any further of antiquitie of perſons, <hi>Succedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, non Petro in paſcendo, ſed Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulo in parricidio:</hi> We ſucceede, not
<hi>Peter</hi> in feeding, but <hi>Romulus</hi> in killing. And ſo is it truely: for you ſhall haue no Pope, that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the people howe to liue in the true feare &amp; loue of God, but ſuch an one as perſecuteth and killeth the Chriſtians, that chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully embrace, and comfortably receiue the glad tydinges of the Goſpell. Thus being comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <pb facs="tcp:176510:33"/> to inſtruct the ignorant, and to feede them with the heauenly word of God, he practiſeth tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie againſt them. Wherfore this is an euident ſigne (that if wee ſhould ſeeme to grant, (which in no caſe is to be graunted) the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> vnto your Biſhop of Rome) that he doeth farre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from the diligence of <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> who had more care to ſaue ſoules, then to become riche &amp; famous in the face of the earth: yea, to haue all men ſubiect vnto him, euen Emperours and kings to kiſſe his foote. Your Pope do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alter from the doings of S. Peter, for Saint Peter neuer warranted to any man the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of heauen for monies ſake: but your Pope, like a good ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, ſetteth all things to ſale, and he that bringeth moſt, ſhal in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen beare the greateſt ſwaye. Wherefore theſe wordes of <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta <pb facs="tcp:176510:33"/> Mantuanus</hi> are true, ſpeaking of the vnhappie ſtate of Rome:
<q>
                  <l>— venalia nobis</l>
                  <l>Templa, ſacerdotes, altaria, Sacra, coronae,</l>
                  <l>Ignis, thura, preces, coelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt venale, Deuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>:</l>
               </q> Amongſt vs in Rome, churches, prieſtes, altars, maſſes, crownes, fire, incenſe, prayer, and heauen are ſet to ſale, yea God himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs may be had for mony. <hi>Budaeus</hi> ſayth,
<hi>Sanctiones Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tificiae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moribus regendis vſui ſunt, ſed, (propemodum dixerim) argentariae faciendae autoritatem videntur ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodare:</hi> The Popes canons ſerue not nowe to guyde mens liues, but, (if I may ſo ſay) they ſerue rather to make a banke, &amp; to get money.
<hi>Bernard of Clunice</hi> ſayeth thus, <hi>Roma dat omnibus omnia dantibus. Omnia Romae cum pretio:</hi> Rome giueth all things to them that giue all thinges. All things at Rome wil paſſe for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Yea euen in the Popes own
<pb facs="tcp:176510:34"/> Decretals, you ſhall find it noted thus, <hi>in ſexto de elect. &amp; electi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtat. fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta in margine, Roma eſt caput auaritiae, ideo omnia ibi venduntur:</hi> Rome is the head of al couetouſnes, &amp; therfore al things there are ſet to ſale. Yea Thomas Becket himſelf (whom you call a ſaint, (&amp; whoſe feſtiual day about Chriſtmas time you keepe with great ſolemnitie,<note place="margin">Gul. Neub. lib. 2. cap. 15 &amp; 25.</note> &amp; a fewe of his bones you keep in ſuch reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God himſelfe is not honored ſo much) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his wilfull diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp; treaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt his prince, he had fled for ayde and ſuccour to Rome, and ſawe that nothing woulde be wrought there without mony) wrote thus thereof to the Biſhop of Menze, <hi>Mater Roma facta eſt meretrix, &amp; proſtituta eſt pro mercede:</hi> Rome our mother is become an harlot, and for money and meede layeth her ſelfe to ſale. To be ſhort, you <pb facs="tcp:176510:34"/> know that our fathers long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were wont to ſay,
<hi>Curia Romana non captat ouem ſine lana:</hi> The court of Rome wil not take the ſheepe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the fliece.<note place="margin">Iohn 2. Matth.
21.</note> Chriſt ſometime thruſt ſuch byers, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, brokers and coarſers out of the Temple: but contrariwiſe, you haue receiued in byers and ſellers, and thruſt out Chriſt, and ſo haue turned the houſe of God into a denne of theeues. Saint Paul ſayth thus vnto the people of Epheſus, <hi>Argentum &amp; aurum nullius concupiui:</hi> I haue deſired no mans golde or ſiluer. Vpon which wordes, in the gloſe it is noted thus,
<hi>Per hoc lupi cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, qui talia concupiſcunt:</hi> Hereby they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſire ſuch things, are knowne for wolues. Saint Hierome ſaith,<note place="margin">Hierom. 1. quaeſt. 1. lib. Nunquam diuinatio.</note> 
               <hi>Quia Prophetae pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniam accipiebant, prophetia eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum facta eſt diuinatio:</hi> For that the Prophets fel to taking of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, <pb facs="tcp:176510:35"/> therfore their prophecy was become a ſoothſaying, that is to ſay, it was of the Deuill, and not of God. This I ſaye, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your dealing, hee that is poore, is not like to go to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich is ſure to be ſaued. Nowe you alledge ſucceſſion of places, not farre vnlike to the Iewes, who will incloſe <hi>orbem in vrbe,</hi> the whole worlde in one citie: but we ſee that God hath choſen many out of Ieruſalem, &amp; the Church is not tyed therunto, &amp; God hath ſuffred by his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will, many Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churches to be turned into the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the Turks, as that of
<hi>Epheſus,</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> &amp; that of Bonne in Barbarie, where <hi>Saint Auſtin</hi> preached, &amp;c. And further it is ſayde there expreſly, <hi>Gloſſa communis in eum verſiculum, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocal.</hi> 12.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of God for a long time, by reaſon of <pb facs="tcp:176510:35"/> the perſecution of Antichriſt, ſhal retire herſelf into the wildernes, as the common gloſe it ſelfe doeth expounde. If euer there were church that might alledge ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of place, it was Ieruſalem, for of it was ſaid,<note place="margin">Deut.
12.11. 2. Sam. 7.10. 1. King. 8.29</note> 
               <hi>Dominus in hoc Templo in aeternum habitabit:</hi> The Lord wil euermore dwell in this houſe. Alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 21.7. Pſal,
132.14.</note> 
               <hi>Elegi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hanc domum, vt nomen meum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in perpetuum maneat:</hi> I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen this houſe, to the end that my name may dwell there for euer. And therefore the Prieſts had no other anſwere to al the Prophets that reprooued them, but this, <hi>Templum Domini,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>Templum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini:</hi> The Temple of the Lorde, the Temple of the Lorde. But ſee what the Lorde himſelfe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto them, <hi>Ite</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ad locum meum in Shiloh, vbi habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit nomen meum a principio, &amp;c.</hi> Go, and ſee Shiloh, I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <pb facs="tcp:176510:36"/> it from the beginning for my houſe: nowe ſee what I haue done vnto it for the wickednes of my people, I wil do euen ſo to the place, which I haue giuen vnto you, and to your fathers. But if you will that I dwell there, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your wayes, &amp; turne from your euil deedes. Now therefore I ſay, if God hath forſaken his owne Temple, for the iniquitie of the Prieſtes, euen then, when he had none beſides erected in the whole worlde, muſt we tye our ſelues to the church of Rome, or to any other place, where all the clymates of the world are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his temple? I can not but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, why any of our countrey men ſhoulde take the church of Rome, to be the mother church of all churches, and the ſame to be an article of our faith. We are not expreſly commanded by the word of God, to acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church <pb facs="tcp:176510:36"/> of Rome, <hi>Caput mundi,</hi> the head of the worlde: neyther is it expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in holy ſcripture, that we are condemned, if we beleeue not at all the traditions of men: but the Scripture manifeſtly doeth<note place="margin">Eſay 29.13. Matth. 15.3. Coloſ. 2.8.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid vs to beleue them. If you can find one only text of the ſcripture, that willeth and commandeth vs to beleeue in the Romane church, as hauing prerogatiue ouer all churches the world throughout, I will be on your ſide to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death. But no ſuch place, I am certain, you can ſhewe in the whole Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the Romane church is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>holy Catholique Church,</hi> which all men (of what countrey ſoeuer they be) muſt acknowledge to be chiefeſt. It is not ſufficient to claime ſucceſſion of place, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs rather to haue regard to the ſucceſſion of doctrine.<note place="margin">Bernard. in Concil. Rem</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, <hi>Quid prodeſt, ſi canonice eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur, &amp; non canonice viuant?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176510:37"/> What auaileth it, if they be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in order, &amp; liue out of order? So ſayeth Saint Auguſtine <hi>contra Donatiſtas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 6. 1. q. 3. Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur canes.</note> 
               <hi>Ipſum characterem multi lupi &amp; lupis imprimunt:</hi> The outward marke, or right of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe many giue to wolues, and be wolues them ſelues. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the auncient father Ireneus giueth vs this good counſell, <hi>Eis qui ſunt in eccleſia praesbyteris, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire oportet, qui ſucceſsionem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ab Apoſtolis: qui cum epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus ſucceſsione chariſma verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis certum, ſecundum beneplacitum patris acceperunt:</hi> It becommeth vs to obey thoſe Prieſtes in the church, which haue their ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Apoſtles, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſucceſſion of the Byſhoprickes, according to the good wil of God the Father, haue receiued the vndoubted gyft of the trueth. Saint Cyprian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe charged for diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:176510:37"/> from his predeceſſours, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth thus,<note place="margin">Cyprian. lib. 2. Epiſt. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Si quis de anteceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus meis non hoc obſeruauit &amp; tenuit, quod nos dominus exemplo &amp; magiſterio ſuo docuit, poteſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitati eius venia concedi: nobis vero ignoſci non poteſt, qui nunc a Domino admoniti &amp; inſtructi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> If any of my predeceſſours haue not obſerued and kept the ſame that our Lord hath taught vs both by his example and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, his ſimplicitie may be pardoned: but we (if we doe the like) can hope for no pardon, being now admoniſhed &amp; inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of our Lorde. Compare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe &amp; order of our churches (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Primitiue church of God, and you ſhall eaſely ſee the right of our ſucceſſion. S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſayeth, <hi>(ad Pompeium contra Epiſtolam Stephani) Si canalis aquae quae copioſè priùs &amp; largiter profluebat, ſubitò deficiat, nonne ad <pb facs="tcp:176510:38"/> fontem pergitur? &amp;c. Hoc &amp; nunc facere oportet Dei ſacerdotes prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta diuina ſeruantes, vt in aliquo ſi mutauerit &amp; vacillauerit veritas, ad originem Dominicam &amp; Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicam, atque Apoſtolicam tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem reuertamur: &amp; inde ſurgat actus noſtri ratio, vnde &amp; ordo &amp; origo ſurrexit:</hi> If the pipes of the conduyte, which before ranne with aboundance, happen to faile, doe wee not vſe to ſearch to the head? &amp;c. The Prieſtes of God keeping Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, muſt doe the ſame: that if the trueth haue faynted or fayled in any point, wee returne to the very originall of our Lorde, and to the tradition of the Goſpel, &amp; of the Apoſtles, that from thence wee maye take the diſcretion of our doings, from whence the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſelfe and originall firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. Thus much touching ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of place. Now I exhorte <pb facs="tcp:176510:38"/> you brotherly to be reconciled to the true church of God, I meane the Church of England, wherein you finde not ſo many idolaters, Necromancers, heretikes, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, Sodomites, churchrob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, periured perſons, mankil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Runnagates, mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophants, Clawbacks, ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tongues, ſcribes and phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as you may eaſely finde in the church of Rome. Boaſt not of the ſucceſſion of your Pope. S. Paul ſayth,<note place="margin">Rom.
10.17.</note> Faith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth (not by ſucceſſion, but) by hearing, and, hearing commeth (not of legacie or inheritance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Biſhop to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, but) of the worde of God. They are not alwayes godly, that ſucceede the godly. Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſucceeded Ezechias, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam ſucceeded Dauid the Prophet. By ſucceſſion, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turke this day poſſeſſeth and holdeth the foure great patriarchal Sees <pb facs="tcp:176510:39"/> of the church, Conſtantinople, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria, Antioch, and Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.<note place="margin">Dan. 9.25. Matt.
24.15. Mar. 13.14. Luk. 21.20.</note> By ſucceſſion, Deſolation ſhal ſit in the holy place, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhall preaſſe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roome of Chriſt. Thus much (welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brethren) touching ſucceſſion of place. Now I will ſpeake a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in confutation of your forged myracles, wherewith you ſeeke to oppugne the true church of Chriſt, and defende your wicked church of Antichriſt, polluted with all maner of deteſtable ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and curſed ſuperſtition. There are two maner of myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,<note place="margin">Miracles.</note> the one true, the other falſe. Myracles are counted falſe, when either they be not that which they ſeeme to bee, or if they be, they are not ſupernatural, but are done by vertue of nature, and that, the Angels either good or bad, three maner of waies may bring to paſſe. For ſometime the <pb facs="tcp:176510:39"/> force of nature which they beſt knowe, they accommodate to the matter, of which coniunction with efficient cauſes folowe the effects, and that ſuddenly, which effectes are of the beholders, thought to bee myracles. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils knowe, that frogs, wormes, or ſerpents bee ingendred of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefacted and rotten things, ſo that there be put heate in certain degrees, in conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, (ſeeing that it is not a hard thing for them to do theſe things which by nature maye bee wrought) it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eaſier to deceiue the weake of beliefe. And by this meanes S.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Trin. lib. 3.</note> Auguſtine thought (as he writeth in his third booke of Trinity) Pharaos Magicians ſometime to haue done the ſame. Moreouer the coniunctions of the ſpirits, of bloud and of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, do much diſquiet mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, from whence proceede the <pb facs="tcp:176510:40"/> ſights or viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of things, which are in thoſe things conſerued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame motion, before they come into the
<hi>phantaſie</hi> or imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and by the ſame reaſon and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wherewith the ſpirit is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, it ioyneth them together, which thing appeareth in ſuch as be Phrentique. Wee are not bound of neceſſitie to beleeue all ſuch myracles whatſoeuer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception. Alexander of Hales ſayeth, <hi>Par.</hi> 4. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 53. <hi>Mem.</hi> 4.
<hi>ar.</hi> 3. <hi>ſolut.</hi> 2. <hi>In ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to apparet caro, interdum humana procuratione, interdum operatione diabolica:</hi> In the Sacrament it ſelfe there appeareth fleſh, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme by the conueyance of men, ſometime by the woorking of the deuill. Likewiſe ſaith <hi>Nicholaus Lyra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyr. in 14. Dan.</note> 
               <hi>Aliquando in eccleſia fit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xima deceptio populi in miraculis factis a Sacerdotibus, vel eis adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus propter lucrum:</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <pb facs="tcp:176510:40"/> euen in the church the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſhamefully deceiued with feigned miracles, wrought either by the Prieſtes, or els by their companions for lucres ſake. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles be not euermore vndouted proofes of true doctrine: therfore Saint Auguſtine ſaith vnto the Manichees, <hi>Miracula non facitis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. 13.</note> 
               <hi>quae ſi faceretis, tamen ipſa in vobis caueremus:</hi> You woorke no my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and yet if you wrought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, at your hands we would take heede of them.<note place="margin">Iere. 23.</note> The Prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie ſaith, <hi>Seduxerunt populum meum in mendaciis ſuis, &amp; in mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis ſuis:</hi> They haue deceiued my people by their lyes, and by their myracles. Aug. <hi>in Ioan. tract.</hi> 23.13. ſaith, <hi>Contra iſtos (vt ſic lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quar) mirabiliarios cautum me fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Deus meus, dicens, In nouiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis temporibus exurgent pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prophetae, facientes ſigna &amp; porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, vt in errorem inducant (ſi fieri <pb facs="tcp:176510:41"/> poteſt) etiam electos: praedixi vobis. Ergo cautos nos fecit ſponſus, quia &amp; miraculis decipi non debemus:</hi> My God hath warned me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of theſe myracle mongers, ſaying, In the laſt dayes ſhal riſe vp falſe prophets, working ſignes &amp; wonders, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end (if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to bring the elect into error: beholde, I haue forewarned you. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bridegrome hath wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs to beware, for we may not be deceiued, no not by miracles. S. Chryſoſt.<note place="margin">In Matth. Hom. 49.</note> ſaith,
<hi>In fine te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poris co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da eſt poteſtas diabolo vt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat ſigna vtilia, vt iam miniſtros Chriſti non per hoc cognoſcamus, quia vtilia faciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſigna, ſed quia om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino haec ſigna non faciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of time power muſt be granted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill to worke profitable mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they worke profitable myracles, but by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they worke no myracles at all. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.
<pb facs="tcp:176510:41"/> ſayth, <hi>Non dicat, Ideo verum eſt, quia illa vel illa mirabilia fecit, vel iſte vel ille, aut quia homines ad memorias mortuorum noſtrorum orant, &amp; exaudiuntur: aut quia illa vel illa ibi contingunt, &amp;c. Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueantur iſta vel figmenta mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um hominum, vel portenta fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſpirituum:</hi> Let no man ſaye, Therefore it is true, for that this man or that man wrought this or that myracle, or for that men make their praiers at the tombes of our dead, and obteine their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, or for that theſe miracles be wrought there, &amp;c. Away with theſe things, they may be either the iuglings and mockeries of deceitfull men, or els illuſions of lying ſpirits. Againe ſaint Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſaith,<note place="margin">In Matth. Hom. 49.</note> 
               <hi>Per ſigna cognoſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur qui eſſent veri Chriſtiani, qui falſi: Nunc autem ſignorum opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio omninò leuata eſt, magis autem inueniuntur apud eos qui falſi ſunt <pb facs="tcp:176510:42"/> Chriſtiani:</hi> In olde tyme it was knowne by myracles, who were the true Chriſtians, and who the falſe: but nowe the working of myracles is taken quite away, and is rather found among them that be falſe chriſtians. Neither is the Goſpel of Chriſt preached this daye vtterly without myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. The blinde ſee, the dombe ſpeake. Your idols are fallen. Your great Babylon is come to ground. Theſe thinges my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, (if you haue eies to ſee) are no ſmall miracles. Saynt Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. ſayth,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in. 1. Cor. hom 8.</note> The conuerſion of the worlde is a miracle. Saint Aug. <hi>De verbo Domini ſecund. Matth. Serm.</hi>
18. ſayeth, <hi>Modo caro cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca non aperit oculos miraculo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, &amp; cor caecum aperit oculos ſermone Domini:</hi> Now a dayes the blind fleſhe openeth not her eyes by the myracle of our Lorde, but the blinde heart openeth his <pb facs="tcp:176510:42"/> eyes at the worde of our Lorde. And againe,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Modo aures corporis ſurdae non aperiuntur: ſed quàm multi habent clauſas aures cordis, quae tamen (verbo Dei penetrante) pateſcant.</hi> Nowe a dayes the deafe eares of the body be not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened: yet many they are, that haue the eares of their heart ſhut vp: which eares notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are opened by entring of the worde of God. Therefore I may rightly ſaye to you with other wordes of Saint Auguſtine <hi>de ciuitate Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 22. ca. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Quiſquis adhuc pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digia vt credat inquirit, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium, qui mundo creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te non credit:</hi> Whoſoeuer yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth myracles to bring him to the fayth, is himſelfe a great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, who ſeeing that the world beleeueth, remayneth ſtill in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe.<note place="margin">Matt. 27.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Whereas the Phariſes ſaid of Chriſt, Let him now come downe from the croſſe, &amp; we will
<pb facs="tcp:176510:43"/> beleeue him. Saint Hierome in Matth. 27. ſayth vnto them,
<hi>Eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi de cruce deſcenderet, ſimiliter non crederetis:</hi> Yea, although he ſhoulde come downe from the croſſe, yet would you not beleeue him. But it were a worlde to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the glorious countenance of your myracles, your croſſes can ſpeak,<note place="margin">Popiſh miracles.</note> your idoles can goe, your i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages can light their own la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes, your holy water is able to calme the ſea, to chaſe away myce, &amp; to make barren women to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue. If you doubt hereof, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferre with Maſter Cope,<note place="margin">Dial. 1. Pag. 18.</note> whome (as I thinke) you knewe aliue, &amp; were preſent at his burial at Rome in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh Church: you knewe him a Canon of S. Peters church at Rome, and one whom Cardinal Hoſius greatly eſteemed. But now both Hoſius and Cope are dead. Conferre alſo with that worthy Prelate the Biſhop of <pb facs="tcp:176510:43"/> 
               <hi>Verona,</hi> your holy father
<hi>Lypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus.</hi> I am ſory, welbeloued, that you are ſo readie to approue your myracles with falſe reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and vnſtable grounds: howbeit ſuch religion, ſuch myracles. Saint Hierom ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ad Algaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> 
               <hi>Mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Antichriſti Chriſti veritas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorabit:</hi> The trueth of Chriſt ſhall deuoure and conſume the falſehood of Antichriſt. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then had their deuiliſh myracles in the temple of their falſe gods, &amp; in effect true, as may appeare by all their hiſtories. Reade Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Liuius in many places.<note place="margin">Et M. Cic.
1. Diuinat.</note> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus, who would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged as Chriſt, wrought miracles. So much touching your miracles. Touching reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; viſions, which are a kind of myracles, wee haue the playne text which decideth this matter: <hi>Cum ſurgens in medio tui Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſomnians ſomnium, ediderit ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi <pb facs="tcp:176510:44"/> ſignum aut prodigium, (quamuis eueniat ſignum illud aut prodigiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quod praedixerat tibi) dicendo, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamur deos alienos, quos non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueras, &amp; colamus eos, &amp;c.</hi> If there ſhall ariſe (ſayeth the Lorde in Deut. 13.) amiddeſt thee a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet or a dreamer of dreames, and that the ſigne or myracle which he hath tolde thee come to paſſe, &amp; thereupon woulde turne thee away to ſtrange gods, &amp;c. thou ſhalt not heare him, &amp;c. There are then both Prophets and viſions true in effect, and yet falſe in their ende, and the tryall of them (as wee may ſee by this text) is the doctrine. Likewyſe when Saynt Iohn (to the ende to keepe vs from falſe prophets) exhorteth vs to proue the ſpirits,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 4.</note> and by and by he addeth, Hereby ſhal you knowe the ſpirit of God, Euery ſpirite that confeſſeth that Ieſus Chriſt is come in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, is <pb facs="tcp:176510:44"/> of God, &amp;c. that is to ſay, Proue the ſpirits by the doctrine which they preach. Therefore Saul &amp; Caiaphas haue prophecied, but (as Saynt Auguſtine ſayeth) as Balaams aſſe once ſpake,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 2 ad ſimpli. quaeſt. 1.</note> &amp; yet for all that, they might haue once ſpoken the trueth: for the deuill himſelf (to colour his lying) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpeaketh the trueth. Howe weake (my brethren) your reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations be, and howe ſmall credit ought to be giuen therunto, there is no man but ſhoulde know. At Rome you haue them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue reuelations daily, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: A poore man there is in the citie of Rome (of whome I doubt not but you haue heard) who maketh men beleeue, that our bleſſed Lady, with her garde of heauenly mayds, ſaluteth him, and hath conference with him dayly. This man is no otherwiſe then a Saynt counted among <pb facs="tcp:176510:45"/> the Ieſuits. The Pope hath him to pray for him, the people regard him as a holy holy man. This man helpeth the citizens, to bring the wood from Tyber ſyde to their houſes: of his gaine hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth nothing elſe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for meat, drink &amp; cloth: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt he giueth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore. Father
<hi>Hieronimus</hi> Ieſuite, repetitour of the Logicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the Engliſh Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie at Rome, reported that there was there dwelling, an old woman (I wil not otherwiſe cal her, for I deale gently &amp; mildely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you) which would (as he ſayd) tell him euery thing that hee had done in his life time, and when he came to her houſe at any time, ſhe would tell one of her maydes (not hauing ſeen him) that there was ſuch a felowe comming vnto her houſe. She alſo foretolde him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhoulde become a Ieſuite. Hee reported in like wiſe, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope <pb facs="tcp:176510:45"/> in diuers matters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her. He praiſed this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; ſayd how ſhe was greatly in fauor with God, who reuealed ſuch hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſecret myſteries vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended thereby the happie ſtate of Rome, that there ſhoulde be ſuch in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> city, as were worthy to receiue theſe reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; viſions: he counted her a Saint. No dout, if one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I knew at Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge in Wales, in the Towne where I was borne, had bene there, they would haue taken him as a Saint, and familiar felowe with Chriſt. For, (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, as he wandred the countrey) he made men beleeue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he woulde tell them their fortune, what thinges had before chaunced in their time, &amp; thinges that ſhoulde happen afterwardes euen vnto their dying day. But this man (as he was wont to ſaye) tooke his reuelations fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pharies: But <pb facs="tcp:176510:46"/> the Romaniſts affirme, that their reuelations come from God, or from ſome Angell or Saint of heauen, where as in very deede, if a man had the ſtraight exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of them, I am perſwaded they would confeſſe, that they haue their reuelations from the Phairies, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuill, as the other had, whereof mention is made. Moreouer, there was a rich man in Lombardy, that had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like reuelations, but farre more excellent then the other: vpon conſideration whereof hee ſolde all that he had, and gaue it to the poore frankly. For it was reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him in a viſion by Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, and the ſame alſo confirmed with the bodyly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our bleſſed Lady, that he ſhould be Pope of Rome, and ſhould tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate the See of Rome into the citie of Hieruſalem. This man, not able to reade, preſumed <pb facs="tcp:176510:46"/> to preach, and gathered vnto him twelue Apoſtles, who (at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement) preached in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. They had many folowers, and ſuch as beleeued him, ſo much the ſooner, for that he told them, that hee had receiued a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation. He was preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Cardinall Bromeo Cardinal of Milaine, who examined him: and when he had tolde this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he was diſmiſt, and ſette at libertie. They counted not this man an heretique, for crediting ſuch falſe reuelations, making himſelfe Chriſt, &amp; chooſing to him ſelf twelue Apoſtles. Oh my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, deceyue not your ſelues, &amp; ſeeke not to deceyue others that meane you no hurt. It is but in vaine to ſwim againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreame. It is not wiſdome to mainteyne an error knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I am ſure your conſciences are burnt with hoate yrons, ſpeaking and mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <pb facs="tcp:176510:47"/> lyes in hypocriſie. Oh giue not your ſelues ouer into repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate &amp; wilful mindes, deſpiſe not the wiſdome of God within your ſelues. Seeke not to be offenſiue and grieuous to any which bee of the Church of Chriſte. Doe what you can, Gods trueth is mightie, &amp; ſhall preuayle. Dagon ſhal fal down headlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before the Arke, the darknes ſhal flee before the light, &amp; the more fiercely ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wiſedome ſhall withſtande, the more glorious ſhal God be in his victorie: the more you doe falſely ſlaunder the faithfull and true meaning miniſters of God, the greater ſhal their reward bee in the heauenly kingdom of Chriſt. If you take my conuerſion to the true church, to be outwardly and not inwardly, and the ſame to be ſpotted with hypocriſie, I may bee ſorye, not for my ſelfe, (as though I were ſuch a one as you <pb facs="tcp:176510:47"/> take mee to be, for GOD kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth it is nothing ſo, his name be praiſed therefore:) but for your raſhneſſe in iudging that which you knowe not. It is God that is the ſearcher of mens heartes, and none other. If I recanted, eyther for feare of puniſhment, or for prefermentes ſake, you mought count me then (if it were ſo, as it is not) to be farre worſe then a Turke or Pagan, who neuer receiued the trueth. Howe can I be a Proteſtant outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and a Papiſt in heart, with a minde to be ſaued? You knowe, that according to your owne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall lawes, no man dare in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon aſſembly deny the Popes authoritie, and afterwardes to name himſelf the member of that church of Rome. I am ſure that no man is a true chriſtian, which with his lippes doeth profeſſe Chriſt, and with his heart doeth <pb facs="tcp:176510:48"/> flatly denye him. As I doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that there is a God, a Trinitie in vnitie to be woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, who hath moſt gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beautified the heauens, moſt plentifully enriched the earth, moſt Angelically created man, who hath ordeyned the heauen to mayntaine life and light, the earth to ſuccour and ſuſtaine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all creatures liuing in land and water, to ſupply his wants, nothing to be reckened &amp; named, which he hath not moſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally giuen vnto man, as appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him lord and ſoueraigne, but them his veſſels and ſeruants. Againſt hunger, (leſt we ſhoulde famiſh) he hath prouided nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, againſt thirſt, (leſt we ſhoulde periſh) he hath ordayned ſauoury liquors. Againſt colde, (leſt we ſhould die in our naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) he hath giuen vs clothing. As I acknowledge the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie <pb facs="tcp:176510:48"/> of God, and confeſſe the vnmeaſurable greatneſſe of his goodnes &amp; loue towardes man: ſo do I verily, from the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my heart, deteſt your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh religion, &amp; embrace the vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed trueth of Chriſtes Goſpell. I cal God to witneſſe, that what I haue already ſpoken with my lippes, that doe I eſtabliſh in my minde. I beſeech you all, (ſuch as haue forſaken the Pope) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to praye for mee, that it would pleaſe God to make me a profitable member of his church, and ſtedfaſt in the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, euen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of my life. So much for Antiquitie, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, ſucceſſion of perſons or place, miracles and reuelations. God of his mercy graunt you, my brethren, true repentance. Nowe good Chriſtian audience, and welbeloued brethren, I will ſpeake a worde or two touching <pb facs="tcp:176510:49"/> the images, which Papiſtes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and haue in their churches. The ſcriptures in ſundry places plainely forbid any image to bee made. The Lorde warned the people of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.15.</note> that they ſhould reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that they ſawe no image in the day that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſpake vnto them in Horeb, out of the mids of the fire.<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.18.</note> And in Iſaiah, <hi>Cui aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milabitis Deum, aut qua ſimilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne illum exprimetis?</hi> To whome then wil you liken God, or what ſimilitude will you ſette vp vnto him? And againe, the Lorde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the ſame,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.9. to the 19.</note> ſaying, <hi>Quis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debit effingere Deum, aut fuſile aut ſculptile facile, quod nihil prodeſt?</hi> Who hath made a god, or molten an image, that is profitable for nothing? Beholde, all they that are of the fellowſhip thereof, ſhal be confounded, for the workmen themſelues are men: let them all be gathered together, and ſtande <pb facs="tcp:176510:49"/> vp, yet they ſhal feare, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded together. I can not a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle maruayle, that among you, my brethren, (I meane the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes) that <hi>Dominicke Aſotus,</hi> writing vpon the Epiſtle to the Romanes, the firſt chapter,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.21.</note> durſt ſo boldly affirme, that in the ſame comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of God, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were not forbidden to make images, repreſenting the fourme of man: for (ſayde hee) the lawe there onely maketh mention of birdes, of fourefooted beaſtes, &amp; of creeping wormes, whereas in very deede they are ſtrayghtly charged not to make the images of male or female. Moreouer it is expreſſed in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.4, 5, 6, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Os ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, &amp; non loquuntur, pedes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, &amp; non ambulant, aures habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; non audiunt, nares, &amp; non odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur:</hi> They haue a mouth, and ſpeake not, they haue feete, and walke not, they haue eares, and <pb facs="tcp:176510:50"/> heare not, they haue noſes, and ſmell not. The Carpenter is bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Iſaiah,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 44.13, 14.</note> which of one part of the hewen tree, maketh an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, of the other parte he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth fire, and vpon the ſame he baketh bread, he carueth and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth much, that he may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the ſimilitude of a man. By all theſe places it doeth manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, that the images of men are vtterly forbidden, which are inſtituted to a religious end: And yet you (though you knowe that all maner worſhipping of images is forbidden by expreſſe teſtimonies of the holy ſcripture) muſt haue them forſooth, (as you ſay) for bookes vnto ſuch as can not reade. What thinke you in making the image of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and God the holy Ghoſt? You knowe God is a Spirite:<note place="margin">Iohn 4.24.</note> whereof it followeth, that you can not expreſſe his forme, with <pb facs="tcp:176510:50"/> lineaments, with paintings and colours. It is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.18. 1. Tim. 2.16. 1. Ioh.
4.12.</note> that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath euer ſeene God. Why then, if he can not be ſeene, or if he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe inacceſſible light, howe can he be pictured? or howe ſhould a picture make him to bee ſeene? Moreouer, God is vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and infinite, but the thinges which are paynted, grauen, or molten, are meaſurable &amp; finite. Likewiſe, Images are made of men, that the abſent, after a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may be thought preſent: but God is euery where, neyther is he abſent from any thing. It is written in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Si aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dero in coelum, tu illic es.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behooueth vs, not to make God preſent, with images, ſeeing he is alwaies preſent, &amp; to al men. The image ſhould with apt ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented. Howe doeth the image of God the father rightly &amp; truly <pb facs="tcp:176510:51"/> repreſent him, whereas he hath no beginning? The images are made by man, and haue a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Who can ſet forth the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of God and his wonderfull woorkes, howe he is neuer idle, but euermore doing that which tendeth to the ſaluation of man? Contrariwiſe, images ſleepe, and doe nothing at all. Moreouer God is altogether wiſedome and knowledge: whereas your ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges feele nothing, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande as much. Saint Paul ſayeth,<note place="margin">Actes 17.29.</note> that we muſt not thinke the Godhead to be like golde or ſiluer, or ſtone grauen by arte. God that made the worlde and all thinges therein,<note place="margin">Actes 7.48.</note> ſeeyng that he is Lorde of heauen and earth, dwelleth not in temples made with handes, neither is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with mens hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to all life and breath, and all <pb facs="tcp:176510:51"/> things. Fortunate doe I thinke thoſe ſtones to be, whereof ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are made, and put vpon your popiſh altars, becauſe they are had in ſuch reuerence and honor amongſt you, whereas other ſtones not vnlike vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreetes, are troden with feete, and ſpet vpon.<note place="margin">Papiſtes obiection.</note> You obiect vnto vs the authoritie of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſay, It is lawfull to paint God in the forme of man: which you ſeeke to proue by the vii. of Daniel,<note place="margin">Dan. 7.13, 22.</note> I behelde (ſayeth the Prophet) till the thrones were ſet vpon, and the ancient of dayes did ſitte, whoſe garment was white as ſnowe, and the heares of his head like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure wooll, his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheeles as burning fyre. In Ezechiel, ſpeaking of God,<note place="margin">Ezech.
1.5.</note> is expreſſed the figure of man. Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah ſayeth,<note place="margin">Eſay 6.1.</note> that he ſawe God ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon a Throne. Moſes alſo <pb facs="tcp:176510:52"/> with the Seniours ſawe God, when hee ſate in his Throne or tribunal ſeate.<note place="margin">Exod. 33.20, 23.</note> And in the mount he ſawe God in the forme of man departing. Seeing theſe things nowe vttered were ſeene of the Prophets, why then is it vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs to paint God with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and karuing?<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſwere."/> I anſwere thus vnto your obiection, The diuerſitie of bodily members, which is aſcribed vnto God in the holy Bible, hath ſhewed in a myſterie, that the Diuine nature ſhould take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and likewiſe it ſignified my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, that God ſhould take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him fleſhe, and become man. Yea (to let this anſwere goe) I ſay, it was the goodneſſe of God, wherewith he ſo applyed himſelf vnto our infirmity, that whereas we could not vnderſtand his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, GOD appeared ſo in the ſight of man, as though hee had <pb facs="tcp:176510:52"/> bene man himſelfe. By his eyes hee deſcribed prouidence, by his armes, ſtrength, by his handes, workemanſhippe, by his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrelles, wrath, and many things of like ſorte. And whereas you ſay that it is lawfull for vs (for the expreſſing of God) to vſe the like lineaments, colours, and caruings, it followeth not. To GOD there is no lawe giuen which hee ought to obſerue, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are all thinges lawfull to men, which he iuſtly and rightly hath done.<note place="margin">Exod. 7.5.</note> God reuengeth him on his enemies,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.2, 10</note> hee giueth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to the father to kill his ſonne,<note place="margin">Exod. 11.2.</note> and he willeth the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues to take with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goods of the Egyptians: which thinges if men ſhould doe or commaund, they could not cleare themſelues of a great offence, committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. The Lorde hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered a law to men, and to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <pb facs="tcp:176510:53"/> hath hee giuen no lawe: for ſeeing that hee is the Authour of the lawe, hee may thereof except what he lyſt. Wherefore it is to be graunted, that hee hath done nothing without conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and infinite iudgement. I woulde gladly bee briefe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I refer you to the chapters which ſpeake againſt Images. Reade <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4. <hi>Leui.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Num.</hi> 33.52.
<hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.
<hi>Eſa.</hi> 40.18. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Heb.</hi>
2.18. <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Baruc.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.42.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 14.3. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Gal.</hi>
5.19. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.5, 21. You ſee, my brethren, in howe many places the ſcripture doeth forbid vs to haue images, yet you will haue them, though God ſay nay, if your holy father the Pope doth allow them. Let vs ſee now what the auncient Doctors and graue fathers haue ſayd by your images.<note place="margin">Tertul. in lib. de Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolatria.</note> Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his booke of
<pb facs="tcp:176510:53"/> Idolatrie, ſayeth, God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden an image as well to bee made, as to be worſhipped. As far as making goeth before wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping, ſo farre is it before that the thing be not made, that may not be worſhipped. Some man will ſaye, I make it, but I wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it not, as though hee durſt not worſhippe it for any other cauſe, but onely for that ſame cauſe, for which he ought not to make it: I meane, both wayes procure Gods diſpleaſure. Nay rather thou worſhippeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image, thou giueſt the cauſe to other to worſhippe it. Some one or other that maintaine idolatrie, wil ſay, And why then did Moſes make the image of the braſen Serpent in the wilderneſſe?<note place="margin">Num. 21.8.</note> The olde ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters founde out and vſed the ſame, aboue fourteene hundreth yeres agoe. One &amp; the ſame God, hath by his generall Lawe both <pb facs="tcp:176510:54"/> forbidden any image to be made, and alſo by his extraordinarie &amp; ſpeciall commandement he hath bidden an image of the ſerpent to be made. If thou be obedient to the ſame God, thou haſt his Lawe, Make y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> no image: but if thou haue a regard to the image of the Serpent that was made afterwarde by Moſes, then doe thou as Moſes did, Make not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny image againſt the law, vnleſſe God commaunde thee, as hee did Moſes.<note place="margin">Origen. libr. 7. contra Celſum.</note> Origen ſayth, We make no image of God, as knowing him to be inuiſible, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out bodie. Againe he ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ibid. lib. 4. contra Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> The minde of the Lawe was this, that they ſhoulde in all thinges ſo behaue themſelues, as the trueth requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that they ſhoulde beſide the trueth, counterfeite nothing, repreſenting the ſhape of a man or woman.<note place="margin">Cyprian in lib. de Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> Cyprian ſayth, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were firſt drawen, thereby <pb facs="tcp:176510:54"/> to keepe the countenance of the dead in remembrance, vpon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof, thinges grewe at length vnto holineſſe, that at the firſt were taken onely for ſolace. Againe,<note place="margin">Ibid. tract. 1. in Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trian.</note> what doeſt thou bowe thy captiue bodie before fooliſh images, &amp; earthly counterfaites? God hath made thee vpright: and whereas all the beaſts of the earth are depreſſed in ſhape, ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe to the groundward, thou haſt a loftie ſtate towardes heauen, and to God thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is erected. Then looke vp thither, thither caſt vp thine eies, ſeeke God aboue, that thou maiſt want hell belowe: lift vp thy doubtfull heart to hygh and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thinges. What doeſt thou throwe thy ſelfe with the deuill, whome thou ſerueſt, into the pit of death? Clement ſayth,<note place="margin">Clement to Iames the ſuppoſed brother of our Lord.</note> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by the mouth of other, is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to bring forth ſuch words, We to <pb facs="tcp:176510:55"/> the worſhip of the inuiſible God, worſhip the viſible images. And this is moſt certeinly falſe. For if you will truely worſhip Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, you ſhould (by being bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial vnto man) worſhip the true image of God in him. What ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God is this, to runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the counterfeites of timber and of ſtone? and to worſhip the ſhapes that are without ſoule, &amp; deſpiſe man, in whom is the true ſhape of God? <hi>Arnobius</hi> in his eight bookes againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles: We neither worſhip, nor wiſh for croſſes: you that conſecrate wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den gods, peraduenture worſhip your wodden croſſes, as partes of your gods. If you had not this image, ſhould Chriſt be ignorant that he were ſerued of you? Will you thinke that there is no honor done him? Then doeth he receyue your ſeruings and worſhippines by certaine traynes, by other put
<pb facs="tcp:176510:55"/> in truſt, &amp; before he, to whome the worſhip is due, haue any feeling of the matter, you doe your ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto the image, and ſend him but the ſcrappes from another mans boorde. And what can be deuiſed more iniurious, ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, &amp; vncourteous, then to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge one God, and make thy ſute to any other thing? to hope for helpe of God, and powre out thy prayers to a ſenſeleſſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage? Is not this (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe ſayth) to haue a quarrell to <hi>Alfonſus,</hi> &amp; fight with
<hi>Ferdinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do?</hi> and where thou ſeekeſt for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of men, to aſke the ſentence firſt of porkelings, and of aſſes? Is not this an errour? Is it not properly a madnes, in trembling wiſe to make thy humble ſute to a thing that thou madeſt thy ſelf? And whereas thou doeſt knowe, and art aſſured, that it is thine owne workemanſhip, the fruites
<pb facs="tcp:176510:56"/> of thine owne fingers, to fall gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueling vpon thy face before it? Very children knowe, that your images haue eyes, and ſee not, mouthes and ſpeake not. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then doeth the holy Ghoſt ſo often teach vs, and admoniſh vs the ſame thing in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as if we knewe it not? For that the very ſhape and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a man ſet aloft, after it once beginneth to bee adored and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of the multitude, it bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in euery man that moſt vile affection of error, that although he find there no naturall mouing or token of life, yet he thinketh ſome god or godly thing is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it, and ſo being deceyued, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the forme that he ſeeth, and partly by the waye of authoritie and credite of the authors &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of it, whome they take to be wiſe, and partly alſo by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and deuotion of the people, <pb facs="tcp:176510:56"/> whome they ſee obedient to the ſame, he thinketh that the image being ſo like a liuing bodie, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be without ſome liuing thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath it. <hi>Lact.</hi> ſayeth in plaine wordes,
<hi>Non eſt dubium, quin reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio nulla ſit, vbicunque ſimulachru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt:</hi> Out of all doubt, there is no religion, whereſoeuer there is an Image. S. Aug. ſpeaking of the image of God the Father, ſayeth thus,
<hi>Tale ſimulachrum Deo fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, nefarium eſt:</hi> To deuiſe ſuch an Image of God, it is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Theodorus</hi> the Biſhop of
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyra</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sanctorum imagines &amp; ſpecies ex materialibus coloribus formari minimè decoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putamus: manifeſtum enim eſt, quod vana ſit huiuſmodi cogitatio, &amp; diabolicae deceptionis inuentum:</hi> We thinke it not conuenient, to paynt the images of ſaintes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> materiall or earthly colours: for it is euident, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a vayne imagination, &amp; the <pb facs="tcp:176510:57"/> procurement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deceytfulnes of the deuil. To like purpoſe writeth <hi>Epiphanius, Eſtote memores dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti filii, nec in eccleſias imagines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feratis, neque in Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coemite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis eas ſtatuatis, ſed perpetuò cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferte Deum in cordibus veſtris. Quin etiam neque in domo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni tolerentur. Non enim fas eſt Chriſtianum per oculos ſuſpenſum teneri, ſed per occupationem men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> My deare childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be ye mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that you bring no images in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the churches, &amp; that you erect vp none at the burials of the Saints, but euermore cary God in your heartes, nay, ſuffer no images to be,<note place="margin">Marke wel</note> no not in your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes. For it is not lawfull to leade a Chriſtian man by his eyes, but rather by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudie or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his minde. For this cauſe <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſayth, The ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of images is vnfit for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt. It is a worlde to ſee,
<pb facs="tcp:176510:57"/> how welfauouredly, and howe towardly touching religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theſe men agree with the fathers, of whom they vſe to vaunt. They bee your owne good, and yet you ſee, how they ſpeake againſt your images. If time ſhould permit, I were able to recite many ſuch places out of the fathers, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of your worſhipping ſuch vaine images. You doe not onely allowe images to be had in churches, but alſo you cauſe them to be deuoutly and reuerently ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and that with the ſame honour that is due to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. One of the Biſhops of the council of <hi>Nice</hi> ſayth,
<hi>Venerandas imagines recipio &amp; adoro, &amp; id perpetuò docebo:</hi> I receiue and worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t images, &amp; this wil I teach. Another ſaith, <hi>Sacras imagines perfectè adoro. Qui verò ſecus confite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, eos anathematizo.</hi> I do perfectly adore the holy ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <pb facs="tcp:176510:58"/> and I accurſe all them that hold the contrary. Another ſaith, <hi>Non ſunt duae adorationes, ſed vna, ipſius imaginis, &amp; primi exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, cuius eſt imago:</hi> There be not two kynds of adoration, but one, which is as well due to the image, as to the paterne of the image. Saint Auguſtine ſayth, <hi>Sic omninò errare meruerunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de conſenſu E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangel. lib. 2. cap. 20.</note> 
               <hi>qui Chriſtum &amp; Apoſtolos eius non in ſanctis codicibus, ſed in pictis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietibus quaeſierunt, nec mirum, ſi a pingentibus fingentes decepti ſunt:</hi> So were they worthy to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that ſought Chriſt and his Apoſtles, not in the bookes of holy Scripture, but in paynted walles. Neither may one mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, if the feyners by Paynters were deceiued.<note place="margin">In Epiſt. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Epiſcop. Hier.</note> The old father <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius</hi> ſayth, It is a horrible wickednes, and a ſinne not to be ſuffered, for any man to ſet vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny picture in the church of the <pb facs="tcp:176510:58"/> chriſtians, yea though it were the picture of Chriſt himſelfe: yet you ſtore all your Temples, and eche corner of them with paynted and carued images, as though without them religion were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth. Thus (good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) you ſee both ſcriptures &amp; fathers againſt you. Forſake then your worſhipping of images. Nowe will I ſpeake a litle, after what maner they worſhip images at Rome. I haue ſeene, and ſo haue you, that on euery altar in Rome, there are ſet vp either Idols or images. In S. Peters church, they haue the image of S. Peter in braſſe, holding out his finger to bleſſe them as they paſſe by: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the which image the people fall downe, and make their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto it, kiſſe his foote, and touch it with their Beades. I would aſke you once again, why they paynt God the Father, and <pb facs="tcp:176510:59"/> God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt. Euen becauſe lay men (when they ſee God to haue a body) ſhoulde thinke God the father, &amp; God the holy Ghoſt to be men, as we be. Their prieſts in Italie for the moſt parte are altogether vnlearned. I deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of ſome of theſe Italian prieſtes in the Italian tongue, whether God the father and God the holy Ghoſt had bodies. They anſwered, Yea. Wel then, ſeeing their prieſts are ignorant in theſe thinges, you may perſwade your ſelues that the ſimple countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are likewiſe ignorant. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pais reader of ſcholaſticall diuinitie at Rome, in the Romane colledge (beeing demanded of Doctor Allen) whether it was as lawfull to worſhip the thing that repreſented, as well as the thing that was repreſented by the Image: This graue &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father anſwered, it was <pb facs="tcp:176510:59"/> lawfull to worſhip the tymber, whereof the Image was made. If this be not idolatrie, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould worſhip that thing which is more fit for the fire or for ſome other purpoſe, then to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no idolatrie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be named at al. Thus much briefly touching images. God giue you a heart to conceiue the trueth. You worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pillar vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the which the cock crew, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter denyed his maſter Chriſte. Why do you thus? What, doe you make the cocke a ſaint? The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes haue made them a cratch or manger, repreſenting the oxe &amp; the aſſe, &amp; alſo the byrth of Chriſt, to the which workmanſhippe of man, they fal down and worſhip. Can you ſhewe me a reaſon, why you ſhoulde kneele before theſe ſtones, or why you ſhoulde kiſſe them, and touch them with your beades? What, haue you canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <pb facs="tcp:176510:60"/> the oxe and the aſſe Saints, &amp; doe you ſaye in your Letanies, <hi>Sancte bos, &amp; Sancte Aſine orate pro nobis:</hi> Saint oxe and Saint Aſſe, pray for vs? Why do ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the thirty pence, which Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das tooke to betray his maſter Chriſt? What, doe you count the thirty pence holy Reliques, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iudas had them, or for that they came from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief prieſts? What, do you make Iudas the traytour a Saint, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe prieſts of the Scribes and Phariſes holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The reliques of Saints are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, as bones &amp;c. they fall downe likewiſe on their knees before them, they crye vnto them, they touch the boxe with their beades, they ſee not the bones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrapped in ſilke, and put in a boxe, or in the altar, in boards, or in Chriſtal. The beades touch not the bones, but the outward boxe. The prieſt may beguyle the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <pb facs="tcp:176510:60"/> putting in the boxe the bones of a dead horſe, or the head of a foxe, in ſtead of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saints bones: for the people ſeeth not what is in the boxe, or wrapped in ſilkes. Why doe the poore men for their aſſes bring offrings to ſtations, as candels, torches, and ſuch like? And why do the poore Romanes bring their aſſes to Churches, &amp; cauſe the prieſtes to ſay a fewe prayers ouer them, and ſprinkle holy water vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Belike, they thinke to get a roome or place in heauen for them, &amp; ſ to ryde vpon Aſſes in heauen, or elſe to get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences of the Pope for their aſſes. In deede they are (as the Prophet Dauid ſayth) <hi>ſicut equus &amp; mula quibus non eſt intellectus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.9.</note> They are like horſe &amp; mule, who haue no vnderſtanding. If I ſhould recite all thoſe Idolatrous practiſes, which I haue ſeene at Rome, a whole day were not <pb facs="tcp:176510:61"/> ſufficient to tell them: but by theſe few things layd downe, you may gather the reſt to be as bad, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſe. Now I will ſpeake a litle of the wickedneſſe of Rome, which you count holineſſe, and make our Engliſhmen that were neuer there, beleeue ſo. Firſt I wil begin with your Cardinals, the pillars of your Church. Haue they not beautifull boyes, with whom they commit the ſinne of Sodom,<note place="margin">Gen.
19.5.</note> as I haue heard by the Romanes, and by a Gentleman who ſerued to Cardinal Sforſie, who trauayled by land with me, from the citie Ancona to Venice? Haue not theſe yong Cardinalles pretie wenches in their palaces, whom in the day time they cal ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their ſiſters or couſins, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night time make them either their bedfelowes or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cubines? And do you not knowe, howe that there was a yong Cardinall a Prince, <pb facs="tcp:176510:61"/> burnt at Rome not long ſince, by a common queane of the ſtewes, &amp; toke from her the french diſeaſe, wherwith he dyed miſerably? Do not your prieſts at Rome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame &amp; puniſhment, openly in the ſight of all men goe to the ſtewes? I haue ſeene them with mine eies, (as I walked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreets) embracing the Queanes. O if a miniſter heere in England ſhould commit ſuch abomination, and ſcape vnpuniſhed, howe woulde you cry out againſt him and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magiſtrates! Yet to ſee your owne prieſts ſo to doe, &amp; your Magiſtrates to ſuffer it, you holde your peace, you ſeeme to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it. What ſhall I ſpeake of your Monkes? Was there not at Rome a whole monaſtery of ſuch as beare a ſiluer croſſe in their hands, &amp; are apparelled in blewe, full of women, that went in habit of thoſe monkes, and were they <pb facs="tcp:176510:62"/> not ſpied at the laſt, and eſcaped vnpuniſhed? Be theſe the holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue renounced the world, and haue vowed chaſtitie? Now of the lay men, becauſe I will not ſtand to diſcourſe vpon euery thing that I recite. How doe the citizens liue? Was there not late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great rich citizen, that had a place to the which reſorted many yong Romane Gentlemen, who committed the ſinne of Sodom one with another, and were they not ſpyed out at the laſt, and did not they all ſcape puniſhment, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one poore man which dyed for all? And did not the Romanes ſaye, that he dyed wrongfully, for that the ſinne of Sodom was but a tricke of youth? Count you me that a light offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">Gen.
18.20. &amp; 19.13.</note> that cryeth vp to heauen to God for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? Moreouer, haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes ſixe ſtreetes full of Curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zants, and harlots, who pay a <pb facs="tcp:176510:62"/> yeerely tribute to the Pope? And be there not throughout al Rome Queanes, who lay out of their windowes carpets, and their gownes, which is a ſigne to them that paſſe by, that there they may haue a woman for money? At Shrouetide, what horrible abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are there practiſed at Rome without puniſhment! Doe not men go in womens apparell, and women in mens apparell? The Gentlewomen out of their win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes throwe roſewater, which is a token to them that paſſe by, that there they may defile their bodyes one with another. What murther is there, inſomuch, that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſit in his wagon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daunger of his life? Theſe words of <hi>Petrus Bembus</hi> are true, <hi>Roma eſt ſentina peſſimorum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum:</hi> Rome is the ſinke of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent varlets. I would not for a great deale of money, but that I <pb facs="tcp:176510:63"/> had ſeene Rome: otherwiſe I ſhould haue ſtood in doubt, leſt I had miſreported ought of them, but what I ſawe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeake I, and teſtifie, and cry with Mantuan,
<q>
                  <l>Viuere qui ſancte cupitis, diſcedite Roma:</l>
                  <l>Omnia cum liceant, non licet eſſe bonum:</l>
               </q> Ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſire to liue godly, depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome: for when al things are lawful there, it is not lawful to be honeſt. Peraduenture nowe, you wil ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pope is a holy man. Although I am indebted vnto him 50. or 60. li. in money, yet wil I not, neither can I but ſpeake the trueth of him, vnleſſe I ſhould ſinne, (which God forbid.) Hath not this Pope, at his hauen citie Ancona, priſed &amp; taken away the marchandize of the Turkes mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, for that one of the Turks had offended one of his ſeruants? The Pope perceiuing the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize to bee of great valewe, tooke an occaſion thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marchants of their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize. <pb facs="tcp:176510:63"/> The emperour of the Turks wrote a letter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, deſiring him to reſtore the goods againe to his marchants: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope refuſed ſo to doe. Wherefore the Chriſtian marchants were in like ſort dealt withal at Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. At Macerata, the Pope put a County out of his poſſeſſion, and gaue it to his own ſonne Iames, whom (of a begger) he hath made a Marques, able to ſpend by the yeere, thirty thouſande crownes, and is richly maried to a Dukes daughter: He gaue the countie for his poſſeſſion, not halfe ſo much as it was worth. There was alſo a monke, who came from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, who at Venice refuſed a hundred thouſand crownes, for two precious ſtones which hee brought with him, who thinking to pleaſe this Pope now liuing, &amp; to get a greater rewarde, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the precious ſtones before this Pope Gregorie, who taking the <pb facs="tcp:176510:64"/> gemmes or precious ſtones, in ſteade of reward, committed the Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke to priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alledging nothing againſt him but this, that hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke his cloyſter, or monaſterie. Maſter Alet (whom you know) hath reported this to bee true: for he knewe this ſayd Monke, as he reported to two Gentlemen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> North that had byn at Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and to mee, and to three other ſcholers. Thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his iniquitie. Nowe I will not ſpeake of the Popes pontificalitie, howe hee is caryed on mens ſhoulders, how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple kneele before him, howe the trumpets ſound, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or double canons are diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and howe the people cry out, <hi>Viuat papa Gregorius:</hi> (Let our diſſembling Antichriſt) Let Pope Gregory liue and reigne ouer vs. You faine (my brethren) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is a purging place for the ſoules <pb facs="tcp:176510:64"/> after this life, wherein they abide and ſuffer the ſelfe ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is in hell, and are in no better caſe (to ſpeake of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) then they of hel. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are farre happier then the damned, for that they of purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory are ſure to be ſaued, and they of hell, are ſure neuer to finde end of their miſerable condition. You ſay, that ſuch as be in purgatorie, may be releaſed, and deliuered to heauen, by the praiers and dirges of ſuch as be on earth. That there is ſuch a place named as Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, you ſeeke to proue by the Scriptures. Firſt out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Maccabees,</hi> where it is read, that good and profitable it was to pray for the dead. From hence you go to Zacharie the Prophet, where it is ſaid in the ninth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Eduxiſti vinctos tuos de lacu, in quo non erat aqua:</hi> Thou haſt deliuered thy priſoners out of the <pb facs="tcp:176510:65"/> dungeon wherein there was no water. Alſo in Eccleſiaſtes the 4. <hi>De carcere atque catenis interdum quis progreditur ad regnum?</hi> Who at any time commeth from priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fetters vnto the Crowne? You alledge the Pſalme, <hi>Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uimus per ignem &amp; aquam, noſque in refrigerium eduxiſti:</hi> We haue paſſed both fire and water, and thou haſt brought vs to a refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing place. Out of the newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament you bring this place, where it is ſaid, that the ſinne of the holy Ghoſt is not forgiuen, neither in this worlde, neither in the world to come. <hi>Ergo</hi> (ſay you) in this life ſinnes are forgiuen, &amp; alſo in the life to come. And out of Saint Matthewe you obiect, Take him, and binde him hand and foote, and caſt him into vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkenes, and there let him ſtay vntill hee hath payde the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt peny. <hi>Ergo</hi> (ſay you) he <pb facs="tcp:176510:65"/> meaneth Purgatorie. Alſo you obiect the hiſtorie of Lazarus and the rich glutton. You al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge moreouer this place of the Apocalypſe, where it is ſayd, that nothing impure and defiled with ſinne, ſhall bee admitted to that holy citie of the Lorde. And you thinke that theſe wordes of S. Paul doe ſerue to your purpoſe, that al knees muſt bowe to God, that be in heauen, in earth, and vnder the earth. Finally, you bring foorth this place of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalypſe, that euery creature in heauen, in earth, and vnder the earth giueth prayſes vnto the Lord. You thinke that theſe, and ſuch like places of Scripture doe make greatly for your purpoſe. But it is knowen, that amongſt you Papiſts there be diuers opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s touching purgatorie. Some ſay that it is a true opinion, and an article of our fayth, to teach, <pb facs="tcp:176510:66"/> and beleeue, that there is a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory: Others there be, who not ſo firmely and conſtantly affirme the ſame, but they either ſuſpect, or thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is ſuch a place. Firſt, I will ſhewe, that Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie belongeth not to any article of our faith, neither is it a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing to bee credited. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I will declare, whether the ſuſpition and opinion of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory ſtandeth with reaſon, and is iuſt. I anſwere vnto them, which ſay it is a neceſſary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and an article of our fayth, to acknowledge that there is a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie: If it were a certaine and firme article of our faith, it ſhould then moſt euidently ſo appeare out of the teſtimonies of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For we do not deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which be fathers, or will make men the authors of the matters of religion. It ſhould be a reproch vnto the holy Ghoſt, <pb facs="tcp:176510:66"/> if we ſhould perſwade our ſelues, that whatſoeuer they write, doth tend to our ſaluation, and that the ſaluation of our ſoules doeth ſtand vpon their wordes. What thing ſoeuer apperteyneth to our ſaluation, the ſame by the vertue of the holy Ghoſt is expreſſed in the Scriptures. Saint Paul to Timothie ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> that the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to conuince, to correct and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſnes, that the man of God may be abſolute, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made perfect vnto all good woorkes. If you doe contende to ſet foorth any good woorke, or any thing neceſſary to be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which may not be confirmed by the ſcriptures, I would take that to be neither good, nor profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, if the Scriptures doe not plainly allow the ſame. We muſt not beleeue your wordes to bee <pb facs="tcp:176510:67"/> true, whereas you ſay, The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles haue not taught all things, which touch the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man. This wil I graunt in politicall, but not in ſpiritual matters, that it ſhould be true, which you ſaye, that all things are not conteyned in Scriptures, which belong to the gouernement of a common weale. But to proue that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wrote ſufficiently touching our ſoules health,<note place="margin">Tertul. de praeſcrip.</note> Tertullian <hi>in libro de praeſcript.</hi> ſayth, <hi>Foelix ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia cui totam doctrinam Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli cum ſanguine profuderunt:</hi> Happy is that church which hath receiued the whole doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with the bloud of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Quae audiui a patre meo, omnia feci nota vobis:</hi> Thoſe things which I haue heard of my father, I haue reuealed vnto you. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that I may returne to my matter, often it is doubted of
<pb facs="tcp:176510:67"/> Purgatory. The Greeke church in the councill of Florentine long ſtoode in doubt. And the common places of the ſcripture, which are brought foorth, to proue this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, let them expound them no otherwiſe then the proper and lawfull interpretation doeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and there ſhall then bee left no place to proue Purgatorie. Saint Cyprian in his firſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe againſt <hi>Demetrian</hi> ſaith thus, After we be once departed out of this life, there is no more place of repentance, there is no more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or working of ſatiſfaction, life is here either loſt or wonne. Euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation is here prouided for, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due worſhipping of God and the fruites of fayth. Saint Auguſtine ſaieth, <hi>de ciuitate Dei. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Quidam nullas poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas niſi purgatorias volunt eſſe poſt mortem:</hi> Some men wil haue no puniſhment to be after death, but <pb facs="tcp:176510:68"/> onely the paynes of Purgatory. Euen in Pauls time there were ſome,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.29</note> that being aliue, were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized for the dead. And by the Council of Carthage. 3. canon 6. it appeareth, there were ſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſed to thruſt the ſacrament into the mouth of the dead body, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereby (as it maye bee thought) to procure ſome reliefe of the ſoule: The words be theſe, <hi>Placuit vt corporibus defuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Euchariſtia non detur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. 3. Can.
6.</note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt enim a domino, Accipite, &amp; edite: Cadauera autem nec acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere poſſunt nec edere:</hi> We thinke it good, that the Sacrament be not giuen to the bodies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. For our Lorde ſayeth, Take and eate: but dead bodies can neyther take, nor eate. Theſe were aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent errours in olde time, as it is eaſie to be ſeene. As for the fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of purgatorie, it ſprang firſt from the heathen, and was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:176510:68"/> amongſt them in that time of darkeneſſe, long before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, as it may plainly appeare by <hi>Plato</hi> and
<hi>Virgil. Plato in Timaeo. Virgil. Aeneid.</hi> 6. in whom you ſhal finde deſcribed at large, the whole common weale, and all the orders and degrees of Purgatorie. Saint Auguſtine <hi>de ciuitate Dei, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi>
7. ſayeth, The olde heathen Romanes had a ſacrifice, which they called,
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum purgatorum:</hi> A purgatorie Sacrifice. You will ſay, The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt haue taught vs purgatorie, (not by any worde that euer they wrote, but) by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is as true, as that S. Peter ſayd Maſſe in Rome with a golden Cope, &amp; a triple crowne, vnleſſe perhaps ſome man will thinke, whereas S. Paul ſayth, <hi>Homines priuati veritate, exiſtima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes quaeſtum eſſe pietatem:</hi> They be men voide of trueth, thinking <pb facs="tcp:176510:69"/> that their gayne is godlineſſe: or whereas Saint Peter ſayth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Per auaritiam fictis ſermonibus nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciantur de vobis:</hi> Through coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, by feyned talke, they make ſale of you: that by theſe words, they gaue vs warning of the very fourme and doctrine of your purgatorie: for better au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities then theſe be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I recken, you can lightly finde none. And whereas you tell vs out of ſome heatheniſh fantaſie, that ſinnes can not be waſhed away, but by long ſpace of time, and payne in purgatory, Saint Cyprian ſaith, <hi>In eodem articulo temporis, cum iam anima feſtinet ad exitum, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediens ad labia expirantis emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit, poenitentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clementiſſimi Dei benignitas non aſpernatur, nec ſeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quod verum eſt:</hi> In that very moment of time, euen when the ſoule is ready to paſſe, and is euen at the lippes of the partie ready
<pb facs="tcp:176510:69"/> to yeelde vp the ſpirite, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our moſt mercifull God refuſeth not repentance, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is truely done, is neuer too late. Saint Chryſoſtome ſayeth, <hi>Latro in cruce, neque vno die opus habebat. &amp; quid dico vno die? Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que breui hora: tanta eſt Dei erga nos miſericordia:</hi> The thiefe on the croſſe needed not ſo much as one daye to repent himſelfe. What ſpeake I of one day? No, he nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not one houre: ſo great is the mercy of God toward vs. Saint Auguſt.
<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 80. ſayeth, If any man depart hence without repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<hi>Imparatum inueniet illum dies Domini, quem imparatum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenerit ſuae vitae huius vltimus dies:</hi> Him ſhall the daye of the Lorde finde vnprouided, whom the laſt daye of this life findeth vnproui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Saint Ambroſe ſayth in his booke <hi>de bono mortis, Qui hic non accipit remiſſionem peccatorum, <pb facs="tcp:176510:70"/> ibi non erit:</hi> He that here in this life receiueth not remiſſion of his ſinnes, ſhal not be there. And S. Hierome <hi>in Lamentationes Ierem. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. Thou ſhalt not goe foorth thence, vntill thou haue payed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt farthing, ſayth thus, <hi>Significat ſemper non exituru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe, quia ſemper ſoluat nouiſſimum quadrantem, dum ſempiternas poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas terrenorum peccatorum luit:</hi> Chriſtes meaning is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come out, for that he muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore paye the laſt farthing, whyles he ſuffereth euerlaſting puniſhment for his ſinnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this worlde. So ſayeth Saint Auguſt. <hi>de ſermone Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini in monte, lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>Donec ſoluas nouiſſimum quadrantem, miror, ſi non eam ſignificat poenam quae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur aeterna:</hi> Vntill thou pay the laſt farthing, I maruaile, but it meaneth that payne, which is called euerlaſting. Hereby, my
<pb facs="tcp:176510:70"/> brethren, I thinke it may partly appeare, that you maintaine your paynted fyre and paper walles, with painted authorities and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per reaſons. Verely the Chriſtian people of the Eaſt church of God, which ſometime was as great &amp; as famous as the Church of the Weſt, notwithſtanding they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued in God, and his Chriſt, &amp; knewe there was both hell &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: yet in your Purgatory they had no ſkil. One of your Doctors ſaith,
<hi>Alphonſus de haereſibus lib.</hi> 8. <hi>de indulgentiis. Vſque in hodiernu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diem Purgatorium non eſt a Graecis creditu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Vntil this day, of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, or of the Eaſt church, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory was neuer beleued. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can not iuſtly ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your fantaſie herein was euermore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted vniuerſal, or catholique. Auguſtine in Pſal. 85. in deede ſometime ſayeth, There is ſuch a certaine place, ſometime he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:176510:71"/> not but there may bee ſuch a one, ſometime he doubteth: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time againe hee vtterly denyeth there is any at all, and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that men are therein decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by a certaine naturall good will they beare their friendes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. But yet of this one er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hath there growen vp ſuch a harueſt of thoſe maſſemongers, that the maſſes being ſold abroad commonly in euery corner, the Temples of God became ſhoppes to get money, and ſilly ſoules were borne in hand, that nothing was more neceſſary to be bought. In deed there was nothing more gainefull for theſe men, then to ſell maſſes for the dead. Your owne Roffenſis ſayeth, <hi>Nemo nunc dubitat Orthodous, an pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorium ſit, de quo tamen apud priſcos, vel nulla, vel quam rariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima fiebat mentio: ſed &amp; Graecis ad hunc vſque diem non eſt credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, <pb facs="tcp:176510:71"/> quamdiu enim nulla eſſet cura de purgatorio, nemo quaeſiuit indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentias:</hi> No Catholique man nowe doubteth of Purgatory, wherof notwithſtanding among the auncient Fathers, there is eyther no mention at all,<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> or very ſeldome, yea euen vntill this day the Grecians beleeue it not, for ſo long as there was no care of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, no man ſought after par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons. So much for Purgatory. Nowe I thinke it not amiſſe (my brethren) ſomewhat to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your praying for the dead. Firſt I wil diſproue your praying for the dead by ſcriptures. Then after, I will confute the ſame by the authoritie of the Doctours. To beginne with Scriptures, I cite the 2. of Samuel
12.22. While the childe was yet aliue, I faſted and wept, for I ſayde, who can tell, whether God will haue mercy on me, that the child <pb facs="tcp:176510:72"/> may liue? But nowe beeing dead, wherefore ſhoulde I nowe faſt? Can I bring him againe any more? I ſhall goe to him, but hee ſhall not returne to mee. Pſalme 49.7. A man can by no meanes redeeme his brother, hee cannot giue his ranſome to God, ſo precious is the redemption of their ſoules, and the continuance for euer. Eccleſiaſtes 9.5. The dead knowe nothing at all, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue they any more reward, for their remembrance is forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and they haue no more porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for euer, in all that is done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne. All that thine hande ſhall fynde to doe, doe it with all thy power: For there is neyther worke, nor inuention, nor knowledge, nor wiſedome in the graue whither thou goeſt. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 1. Theſſalon. 4. I woulde not haue you ignorant, brethren, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them which are aſleepe, <pb facs="tcp:176510:72"/> that you ſorrowe not euen as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which haue no hope:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.13.</note> for if we beleeue that Ieſus is dead, &amp; is riſen, euen ſo them which ſleepe in Ieſus, will God bring w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Wherefore comforte your ſelues one another with theſe woordes. Thus much for ſcripture. Nowe will I alledge the ancient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Fathers.<note place="margin">Cypr. ſerm. de mort.</note> Cyprian in his ſermon of mortalitie ſayth thus, Seeyng that we knowe, that our brethren, which bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of this worlde, by the hande and calling of the Lorde, are not loſt, but ſent before: wee muſt not here take on vs blacke gownes, ſyth that they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready there put on whyte gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: we muſt not giue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vnto the Paynims, that they may deſeruingly, and by good ryght blame vs, or lay to our charge, that we doe lament, and bewayle them, as periſhed and <pb facs="tcp:176510:73"/> loſt, whome wee doe affirme to liue with God, and ſo to proue with the teſtymonies of our hearts, and breake the ſame faith that we doe profeſſe and ſet forth by our communication &amp; talke. Againe hee in his firſt treatiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Demetrian, When we bee once departed out of this life, there is no more place of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, there is no more effect or working of ſatiſfaction, life is here eyther loſt or wonne, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation is here prouided for by the due worſhipping of God, and the fruites of faith: then we ſhall bee without the fruite of repentance, &amp; griefe of payne. In vaine ſhall weeping bee, &amp; prayer ſhal be of no force or effect. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine in his firſt booke and 12. chapter of the time:<note place="margin">Auguſt. De temp.</note> Therefore all theſe thinges, that is to wit, the looking vnto the corpes, or caring
<pb facs="tcp:176510:73"/> for it, the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the burying, and the pompe of the funerals, are rather for the comforte of the liuing, then for the ayde and helpe of the dead. If coſtly and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous burying doe profite the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, vyle burying, and none at all ſhall hurt and hinder the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The multitude of ſeruants did in the ſight of men make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and glorious funerals vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that rich man that was all clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in purple: but the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Angels made much more excellent and noble funerall in the ſight of God, vnto the poore ſilly creature that was ful of ſkabbes, blaynes and ſores: for they did not lay him in a tombe of marble, but did cary him into the boſome of Abraham. Likewiſe in his fyrſt treatiſe vpon the Epiſtle of Iohn, Whereof doe Schiſmes come? Hereof they come, when men ſay, We are righteous, we <pb facs="tcp:176510:74"/> doe pray, we doe obteine. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom in his 13. queſt. and 2. chap. We knowe that in this worlde wee can be helped one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eyther with prayers, or with counſell: but after wee bee once before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, neyther Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, nor Noah be able to pray for any body, but euery man ſhall beare his owne burthen. The councill of Toledo. 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.23. <hi>qu.</hi> 2. <hi>cap. qui diui.</hi> We doe bidde &amp; commaunde, that they which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this life by the diuine calling of the Lorde, bee caryed foorth to their graues, onely with Pſalmes: for we doe altogether forbid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame prayer of funerals, that they be wont to ſing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly for the dead. <hi>Item ſenten.</hi> 4. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 45. <hi>Neque.</hi> Hee that prayeth for a Martyr, doth wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto the Martyr. Againſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the dead, I thought it <pb facs="tcp:176510:74"/> ſufficient to ſpeake thus much. Nowe I will ſpeake a worde or two of praying to Saintes. Firſt the Scripture forbiddeth it: for it is written, Pſalme 80.11. Giue vs help againſt trouble, O Lord, for vaine is the helpe of man. Pſalme 115.17. The dead praiſe not the Lorde, neyther they that goe downe into the place of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Eſay 63.16. Doutleſſe thou art our father, though Abraham be ignorant of vs, and Iſrael knew vs not, yet thou, O Lord, art our Father, and our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Nowe for the fyrſt. If the helpe of man bee in vayne, why then do you pray vnto Saintes? And, If the dead praiſe not the Lorde, to what ende then ſhould they be prayed vnto? If Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Iſrael (who were counted holy in the ſight of God) knewe not of them that were in earth, ſhall wee thinke that other <pb facs="tcp:176510:75"/> Saintes haue preeminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt? No, no, we deceiue our ſelues, and the trueth is not in vs. Iere.
15.1. Though Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Samuel ſtoode before mee, yet mine affection coulde not bee towardes this people. Thus ſayeth the Lorde, Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſhe his arme, and withdraweth his heart from the Lorde. Ezechiel 14.14. Though theſe three men, Noah, Daniel, and Iob were among them, they ſhoulde deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe, (ſayeth the Lorde) yet I am the Lorde thy God, which brought thee from the land of Egypt, and thou ſhalt know no God but me, for there is no Sauiour beſides me. Eſther 14.3. O my Lorde, (thou onely art our King) helpe me deſolate woman, which haue no helpe but thee. Matth.
11.28. <pb facs="tcp:176510:75"/> Come vnto mee all yee that are weary &amp; laden, &amp; I will eaſe you. Iohn 14.6. Ieſus ſayde, I am the way, and the trueth. No man commeth vnto the Father, but by mee. To the firſt. If Gods <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wrath kindled againſt his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple coulde not be pacifyed at the interceſſion of Moſes and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, who were Saintes, howe can you perſwade your ſelues, that Saint George or Saint Gregory, or any other Saint may be heard of God praying for you? To the ſecond. Here is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of God pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that put their truſt and confidence in man. But you put truſt &amp; confidence in ſaintes, who interpretiuely bee men. <hi>Ergo</hi> this curſe toucheth you. Theſe holy men, Noah, Daniel, and Iob can doe no more but ſaue their owne ſoules, they can not with their prayers procure the <pb facs="tcp:176510:76"/> ſaluation of other mens ſoules. Theſe three were Saintes, and in fauour with God, as others be, they had the viewe of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious maieſtie of God as others haue: <hi>Ergo</hi> I inferre, If there coulde no helpe be found in them, then you may be aſſured, no helpe is to be founde in others. To the
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> thirde. God telleth vs there is no other Saluation beſides him, but you (my brethren) hope to bee ſaued through the clemencie of your Patrones that be Saynts: wherefore I conclude, that you breake the commaundements of GOD, when hee ſayeth that none can ſaue you, but hee alone. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> To the fourth. The deſolate woman tooke GOD onely to bee her king, (&amp; not ſome Saint or other) her ſhield, her buckler, her defence, her comforter &amp; hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. In this her diſtreſſe &amp; neede, ſhe ranne not vnto ſome Saint <pb facs="tcp:176510:76"/> to craue helpe at his handes, but vnto God himſelf, who was moſt ready to graunt her requeſtes. Therefore you are much to bee blamed, that you will not follow the allowable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of others. To the fift. Chriſt biddeth vs,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> when wee are driuen to anye ſtraights, or are grieued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any kinde of troubles, to make our praiers vnto him, and not vnto Saints, for he maketh no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof: and hee promiſeth that our petitions ſhall be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in his ſight. Seing that of his bountifulnes hee willeth vs to come vnto him, why come you not to him, why goe you vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? O ſtubburne and froward generation, O vnthankfull, and diſloyall ſubiects! You will not come when as you are bidden, you wil not receiue Gods gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of himſelf offred, but ſeeke to craue of his ſeruants, againſt his <pb facs="tcp:176510:77"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> will and pleaſure. To the ſixt. Chriſt telleth vs, that no man can come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father but by him. If no man can come to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by Chriſt, <hi>Ergo</hi> in vayne do you then make your prayers vnto Saints. Act. 4.12. Neither is there ſaluation in any other: for among men there is giuen none other name vnder heauen, wherby we muſt be ſaued. Rom.
10.14. How ſhall they cal on him, in whom they haue not beleeued? Iames 1.5. If any of you lacke wiſdome, let him aſke of God, which giueth to al men liberally. Euery good giuing, and euery perfect gift is from aboue, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth downe from the father of lights. You ſee in theſe places of ſcripture God telleth vs playnly, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaued (by any other, neither by this Saint nor that Saint) ſaue onely by Ieſus Chriſt. Thus much out of the
<pb facs="tcp:176510:77"/> ſcriptures. Now let vs ſee what the Doctors ſpeake againſt your praying vnto Saints. Firſt I wil begin with Auguſtine in his ſecond booke and 8. chap. againſt the Epiſt. of Parmenian. Saint Paul maketh not himſelfe a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour betweene God and the people, but requireth that they pray all one for another, being all the members of Chriſt. If Saint Iohn would ſaye, This haue I written vnto you, that you ſinne not, and if you ſinne, you haue me your mediatour before God, and I will intreate for your ſinnes, as Parmenian (the heretique) in a certaine place, made the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop a mediatour betweene God and the people: what good and faithfull chriſtian man could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide him? Who would looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as the Apoſtle of Chriſt? or rather who would not thinke him to bee Antichriſt? Alſo vpon <pb facs="tcp:176510:78"/> the 108. Pſal. All praier, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not made vnto god by Chriſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth not put away ſin, but alſo is turned into ſinne. Item in his 3. booke of freewil. Wee are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to goe to any creature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be made bleſſed, but to the creator &amp; maker of al things, of whom (if we be perſwaded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth is) we are deceiued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a damnable error. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his booke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit &amp; the ſoule, 29. cha. The ſoules of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are dead, are there where they do not ſee, neither heare what thinges are done, or chaunce in this life: Such is their care for the liuing, that they know not what we do, euen as our care is for the dead, that wee knowe not what they doe. Item, in his tenth treatiſe vpon Iohn. My mother whome you haue called bleſſed, therefore is bleſſed, becauſe ſhe hath kept the worde of GOD, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <pb facs="tcp:176510:78"/> in her the word was made fleſhe. Item, in his booke of the remiſſion of ſinnes, the 14. chap. The Apoſtle ſaid truely, Bee you folowers of me, as I am of Chriſt He neuer durſt ſaye, Bee you iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified of mee, as I am iuſtified of Chriſt. None is iuſt, but Chriſt iuſtifying. Therefore he ſayd, He that beleeueth in him that iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the vngodly, his fayth is counted for righteouſnes. Who is ſo bolde therefore to ſaye, I iuſtifie thee, which may not bee ſaid of the Saints, but of the holy of holieſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaid, Beleeue in God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.7.</note> beleeue alſo in me? Againe in his firſt treatiſe vpon the Epiſtle of Iohn: From hence commeth ſchiſmes, when men ſay, We are righteous, we make holy the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, we doe iuſtifie the wicked, we doe pray, we do obtaine. <hi>Item</hi> in 84. treatiſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohn. Though we dye brethren for brethren, yet <pb facs="tcp:176510:79"/> the blood of no Martyrs is ſhed for the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, which thing Chriſt hath done for vs. Ambroſe vpon the 1. chapter of the Romanes: But we obteine Gods fauour, from whome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſecret, as knowing what euery man is meete to haue, wee neede no ſpokeſman, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout minde, for whatſoeuer ſuch a one ſpeaketh vnto God, God wil anſwere him. Chryſoſt. in his 2. hom. of the woman of Canaan: Tell mee woman, ſith thou art a wicked and ſinfull woman, how durſt thou go vnto him? I know (ſayth ſhee) what I do. Beholde the wiſedome of the woman, ſhe prayeth not vnto Iames, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth not Iohn, ſhe goeth not vnto Peter: ſhee did not get her ſelfe to the company of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſhee ſought for no mediator: but for all theſe things, ſhe tooke repentance for her companion, <pb facs="tcp:176510:79"/> which did fulfill the roome and place of an aduocate: and ſo ſhee did goe to the high fountaine. Item in his ſermon of going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Goſpel: There is no neede of a Porter, of a Mediator or miniſter, no neede of Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates with God, nor of any run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and gadding about for to ſpeake fayre vnto other: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou be alone, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an aduocate, and praye vnto God by thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne thy petitions. Cyrill in his booke of right faith: He was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp into heauen: but as God he is ſhewed to graunt the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them that worſhip him, if they make their prayers in his name. For why is it more meete to giue Saints their aſking, and to graunt them their petitions, then for him, which is onely by his owne nature, &amp; truely God? Leo Biſhop of Rome, in his 81. <pb facs="tcp:176510:80"/> Epiſtle: Although the death of many Saintes hath bene preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſight of the Lorde, yet the killing of no Innocent, hath bene the propitiation for the worlde. The righteous receiued, but gaue no crownes, and out of the valiantnes of the faithful are grauen examples of patience, not giftes of righteouſneſſe. For their deathes were euery one ſinguler to himſelfe, and none of them did by his ende paye the debt of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, foraſmuch as there is our Lord Chriſt, in whom all are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, all dead and buryed, and raiſed vp againe. Eraſmus in his booke called the Preacher: If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man lacke wiſedome, let him aſke it of God, and not of the Saints. So much againſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto Saintes. Here in the firſt parte of my declaration, I haue (as you knowe) declared a true report of the wickedneſſe of <pb facs="tcp:176510:80"/> Rome: I beganne with the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals liues, proceeded to the Prieſtes, Monkes, and citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and ended with the Pope. Seeing you know theſe reportes to be true, for your owne ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on returne to the trueth. Bee not obſtinate and frowarde in your falſe opinion. You are courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gently intreated, yet are you neuer the better, but rather the worſe, like Frogs that keepe a great crooking &amp; ſturre againſt the light of the Sunne: ſo do you againſt the glorious and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table beames of Chriſt his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. Be ſatiſfied with trueth, and abuſe not the mercifull lenitie of our gracious Soueraigne, leſt that the Lordes diſcipline be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, which ſhall reſtraine your ſpreading poyſon, and auoyde the hazard whiche otherwiſe ſhould happen, not onely to the church of God amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, (which
<pb facs="tcp:176510:81"/> might not thriue amidſt ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berſome weeds) but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the enda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gering (which the Lorde of glorie turne from vs) of this floriſhing common weale, &amp; her Maieſties moſt royal perſon, crowne &amp; dignitie. Your malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; curſed practiſes, as cocatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, haue brought forth &amp; hatched great dangers to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale already. If you ſhould be ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, without recantatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcape vnpuniſhed, winked at, fauoured and ſpared: greater miſchiefe ſhal inſue your treaſonable practiſes, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ruine and deſolation of this bleſſed lande, which God of his mercie turne awaye from vs. What peſtiferous bookes haue our Engliſh fugitiues thruſt foorth vnto vs, defacing Gods holy trueth, the Queene her roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſtie, many of her hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable counſell, and ſundry of her louing and faithfull Subiects?
<pb facs="tcp:176510:81"/> Haue thei not alſo procured Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, Pope <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> to exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate our Redoubted Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, &amp; al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, chriſtianly &amp; quietly to liue vnder her gouernment? But an vnderſerued curſe hurteth not. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Midſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer laſt was twelue-month, they renued theſe bulles of excommunication, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by this Pope Gregory, vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor &amp; name of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. There were fiue hundreth copies printed at Rome, as two of you (my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) can verifie the ſame, and how they were publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as I heard at Rome, in the Engliſhe Seminarie at Rhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and were put faſt to pillars in the citie. Theſe Bulles of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication were ſcattered throughout all Italie, Spaine, &amp; parte of Germanie. In theſe buls of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (forſooth) they haue diſcharged (if their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſhoulde bee credited) her <pb facs="tcp:176510:82"/> highneſſe Subiects from their loyaltie &amp; obedience to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, their natural Prince. Haue not their Bulles pronounced her Maieſtie to be no lawful Queen, whom God hath placed ouer vs? Haue not their attemptes bene the ſeede of rebellion? and haue they not cauſed, and doe cauſe to this day, many to practiſe ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her graces deſtruction?<note place="margin">The loyaltie of Papiſts.</note> One of your Readers in Diuinitie poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, I am certayne, before two hundreth ſcholers, and not ſo fewe, as one of you may teſtifie the ſame, moſt impudently and deuiliſhly ſpake, that it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man of worſhip in Englande, to giue authoritie to the vileſt wretch that is, to ſeeke the death of our ſoueraigne Queene. But God who hath defended her, ſtill preſerue her: And then let K. P. who threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and Antichriſt, Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory <pb facs="tcp:176510:82"/> an Italian borne in the citie of Bolonia, who prouoketh, ioyne their powers together: yet ſhee ſhall preuayle, to their ſhame, &amp; to her honour. Father <hi>Pais</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard borne, reader in ſcholaſtical diuinity in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romane colledge at Rome, ſaid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of three hundreth ſcholers at leaſt, theſe were his woordes, <hi>Bona Papae voluntas trita &amp; manifeſta eſt, &amp; eius crumena parata, ſed R. P. aut metus ſubtrahit, aut poteſtatis defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus vetat, vt ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Angliam exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum ducere non audeat.</hi> That is, the Popes good will is tried and knowne, and his purſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but K. P. either feare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth, or power forbiddeth him that hee dare not venter, to bring his Army of Souldiers into Englande. But leaſt that I be too tedious to my hearers, of this firſt part I wil make an end, <pb facs="tcp:176510:83"/> beſeeching you my brethren to become loyall and faythfull to your naturall Prince, forſaking your ſuperſtitious Idolatrie and curſed religion, your pompous glorie, and prowde hierarchie, and thus much for the firſt part.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Qui veniunt ad vos veſtitu ouium, &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which come vnto you in ſheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>In this place (being the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of my diuiſion) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt biddeth vs: Beware of falſe prophets, he addeth alſo a note or marke, to know them by, in theſe words: Which come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in ſheepes clothing. In the firſt words, which come vnto you, there is alſo giuen vs one mark of a falſe prophet, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to go before he be ſent, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt words, In ſheepes clothing, is ſhewed, that when falſe prophetes come, <pb facs="tcp:176510:83"/> it is but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> flatterie &amp; diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For to come in ſheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: is nothing elſe, but to feine himſelfe a ſheepe, that is, to make thy ſelfe holy, whereas thou art nothing leſſe, to name thy ſelfe a follower of Chriſtes holy worde, wheras thou art obedient to the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to name thy ſelfe a Prophet, whereas y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art not, to name thy ſelfe a teacher of the trueth, wheras thou art a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of lies: to reſemble a ſheepe in outward ſhew, but in wardly to be a Foxe. What a falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is, you may know if ye reade theſe places of ſcripture that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to witte, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.
<hi>Ierem.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.34. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.4. and the 2.
<hi>to Timoth.</hi> 3. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.
<hi>Rom.</hi> 16. For whiles they giue themſelues vnto couetouſneſſe, (and that vnder a colour of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,) what can otherwiſe fall out, then that which S. Peter <pb facs="tcp:176510:84"/> ſayth, With fained wordes they ſhoulde make marchandize of Gods people.<note place="margin">2. Pet.
2.3.</note> So did the falſe Prophetes amongſt the Iewes: ſo did their ſacrificers, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.5. with them, as our maſſemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers haue done with vs. What maner worſhipping of God haue they feyned? what ſnares haue they laide? namely Indulgences, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, watchings, maſſes for the dead, workes of ſupereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; in fine to that paſſe they brought it, that obſcured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of our redemption, wherewith al ſuch as beleue, by Ieſus Chriſt are freely redeemed, and get e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. No man thinketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Papiſtes, but they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſerue eternall life (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their owne workes:) or els if their outward workes fayle, to be damned for euer. This is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame diabolicall perdition, with the ſway whereof, a great part of <pb facs="tcp:176510:84"/> Chriſtendome is caried headlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. And the cauſe hereof is, that men haue ytching eares, and therfore procure vnto themſelues heapes of teachers,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.5.</note> to feede their fonde humors, men are highminded, ſelf willed, louers of themſelues, beyng wedded to their owne wayes, and marryed vnto their owne deuices, they leaue the law of God, and follow after the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men. What (I praye you) is the cauſe, that there be ſo many papiſtes in England? is it not, becauſe the true preachers are not beleeued? The trueth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth them, the Scriptures miſlike them, they are delighted with falſehoode, and content to ſtaye themſelues vpon mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions. Preceptes are giuen, &amp; yet the precepts of God are not regarded, enſamples abounde, and yet the enſamples of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant &amp; faithfull martyrs of God <pb facs="tcp:176510:85"/> are derided and ſcoffed at, the wholſome counſels of the godly eyther are lightly contemned, or elſe heard with ſo ſmall profite, that they enter in at the one eare, and goe out at the other. Is it then to be maruayled, if Chriſt ſuffer theſe pretenſed prophetes, (the Papiſts I meane) to ſeduce them from his trueth? reade 1. of the kings 22.22. In Achab the like hath bene done before, and in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.28. we reade of them that buylded with vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter. Seeing then that they will not giue credite vnto Gods worde, and therewith be contented, God is not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if (that theſe falſe prophetes deceyuing them with an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhewe of holineſſe) he giue them vp to ſtrong deluſions,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.11</note> that they fall from the trueth to error, from light vnto darkenes, from heauen to hell. Such as <pb facs="tcp:176510:85"/> teach them the trueth, are deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and others that inſtruct them in the dregges of idolatrie, are eſteemed and had in great repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Theſe falſe prophets, that they may bring theſe carnal men vnto perfection: they tell them how their forefathers liued, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they embraced papiſtrie, howe that in comming to Churches, they were very diligent, in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of images they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute, howe paynefull in viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting holy places, howe liberall vnto the poore, howe mercifull to the afflicted, and laſtly, howe carefull they were to keepe Gods commandements. Where be all theſe good workes (ſaye they) what is become of them? Nowe one man ſeeketh to beguile ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one man ſpeaketh euill of an other, their deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the church is waxen colde, charitie towards the poore is more then frozen. &amp;c. <pb facs="tcp:176510:86"/> And whereof (ſay they) procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this heape of all miſchiefe, the ripenes of this impietie what roote hath it, ſpringeth it not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corrupt doctrine of the newe fangled Preachers? Vnto all theſe ſuppoſed cauilles, and moſt manifeſt ſlaunders (for other are they not, but ſlaunders and thoſe meere ſuppoſed) I anſwere, whereas they ſpeake of the godly liues of their forefathers (if their liues had bene holy) theſe their good works, whereof they boaſt, were not vndoubted markes of true religion. For reade the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoryes of the Gentiles, let the liues of the olde Philoſophers both Greekes and Latines bee peruſed: and it ſhall not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be gayneſayed, that for the ciuill ſtate of their life, and the morall vertues, they lyued as vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly as euer your forefathers did: yea, and that in ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, <pb facs="tcp:176510:86"/> that ſome of them were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen beautified by the names of the vertues themſelues: as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates the Conſtant, Plato y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, Regulus the promiſe kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Cato the ſober, and ſuch like: yet neyther did their liues proue their religion to be true, neyther was heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> able to be ſcaled by ſo ſhort and weake a ladder. As for that they blame the liues of them that profeſſe the Goſpell, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon inferre that they haue no true religion, they ſpeake more (by their leaues) then trueth wil warrant. For the imperfections of Gods children, and the ſinnes of particular men, are not auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to diſherite them of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:<note place="margin">Gen. 9.2. &amp; 19.33. 2. king. 11. &amp; 12. Matth 26.72.74.</note> as the drunkennes of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, the inceſt of Lot, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adultery &amp; murther of Dauid, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backſliding of S. Peter, &amp;c do declare, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſay they ſinned, &amp; therfore they were not in the right way, were <pb facs="tcp:176510:87"/> to conclude very impertinently, &amp; without all rule of reaſon. Now wheras vpon this weake ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an vntruth, ye miſreport of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſaying, that they allow all licentiouſneſſe of life, it is cleane contrary, for they dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly exhort the people to amendement of life: they condemne not good workes, no, they commend them highly. herein truely you and they do dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: they make workes to followe faith as the fruites, according to that S. Auguſt.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de fide &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus. cap. 14 &amp; epiſt. 106.</note> ſayeth, <hi>Opera ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur iuſtificatum non praecedunt iuſtificandum:</hi> You make workes the grounde and faith the roofe, putting the cart before the horſe, and heate before the fyre. The Queene goeth before, &amp; her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maydes folow, not that ſhe is not able to go without them, but that as neceſſarily to the Maieſtie &amp; Royal port of a prince ſuch atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance <pb facs="tcp:176510:87"/> is neceſſary: ſo is it in faith, and works. You my brethren ſay that good workes are neceſſary, thereby to merite heauen and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ſaluation. But as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are flat againſt you, euen ſo are the doctours alſo, none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do beare with you, they all beare againſt you. We teach the people trueth, you fables. Wee preach faith, and yet exhorte vnto good workes, you ſeeke more for the huſke then for the kernel. We are not ſuch as <hi>Cardinall Hoſius</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemeth vs to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, naughtie and euil preachers, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preach wee any thing that Gods worde alloweth not. How your Elders and our forefathers liued, it ſtandeth you in hande to conſider of: they put their ſonnes into monaſteries, &amp; their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnto Nunneries, what they did they haue anſwered, if they did well, they are pardoned by <pb facs="tcp:176510:88"/> mercie in the promiſe made vnto Abraham: if euil, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal haue a crowne but hee that fighteth lawfully. yet herein ye offer them a great deale of wrong, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as blind guides leading them into by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathes, robbing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, ſpoiling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the trueth of Gods worde, ye put the ſheepe to anſwere for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blindneſſe of the ſhepheard. That they liued in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance it can not bee denyed, it was not of faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> for it was not grounded vpon the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word of God: They did as they were taught, if they had bene taught better, better woulde they haue done, yet is it not fit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne any mans ſeruant whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſtande or fall. Neither is their early riſing to <hi>Mattens,</hi> to their <hi>Complyn</hi> at midnight, their going barelegged and barefoote, their faſting and wilful pouertie, their hard lying, their whippings <pb facs="tcp:176510:88"/> their going in ſackecloth, their lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g praying in the ſtreetes, nor all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like practiſes able to drawe vs from the trueth. nay what wil ye anſwere when God ſhall aſke you,<note place="margin">Eſa. 10.12. Mat. 15.9.</note> Why did ye worſhip me with mens traditions? who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired this at your handes? Reade the booke entituled, <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolomitanus peregrinus,</hi> you ſhal finde, that the Turkes liue more auſterely in their Monaſteries and abroad, then euer any of you did. It were too long to rehearſe their outwarde godlineſſe, they faſt and pray as you doe, they build Temples, they maintayne hoſpitals, they viſit the ſicke, they pray in the night time more then you doe, and the day tyme they ſpend either in prayer, or in ſome good woorke. They clothe the naked, feede the hungry, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor the harborleſſe, they followe you in al points of good woorks, <pb facs="tcp:176510:89"/> yea, and they farre ſurpaſſe you. For proofe hereof, I referre you to the reading of their Hiſtories. yet will ye not ſay (I thinke) that the Turkes for all their good workes are like to bee ſaued. If this were a good argument, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by good works men are ſaued: then could I reaſon thus:
<q>The Turkes do good works, But they which doe good workes ſhalbe ſaued: <hi>Ergo</hi> the Turkes ſhalbe ſaued.</q> And whereas you ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they did well which make their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Nonnes. For (ſay you) they ſerue God and our Ladie: if their ſeruice be good &amp; commendable, ſeeing that they attribute and apply that vnto our Lady, which (in Dauids Pſalmes) is ſpoken of God the father and the ſonne, iudge you. For when they pray, they pray after this maner, <hi>In te domina ſperaui, miſerere mei do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina, <pb facs="tcp:176510:89"/> dixit dominus dominae meae, ſede mater mea a dextris meis, &amp;c.</hi> In thee O Lady haue I truſted, O Lady haue mercie vpon mee, the Lord ſaid vnto my Ladie, ſit my mother at my right hand, &amp;c. In ſuch ſort, that theſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which they call our Ladies houres, were the chiefe deuotion of thoſe that were moſt deuoute. Nowe ſeeing the bleſſed virgin was put in Chriſts place: I aſke what remayneth for him? and if, becauſe ſhee bred hym and bare him, and brought him forth, ſhe accompliſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluation of thoſe that cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her, what then was there, that he ſhould deliuer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to death for vs? But let mee (I praye you) ſpeake a worde or two, concerning the doctrine of theſe falſe prophets, which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth a man to be iuſtified by his good workes. If I ſhould iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelfe, myne owne mouth
<pb facs="tcp:176510:90"/> ſhall condemne mee (ſaith Iob:<note place="margin">Iob.
20.</note>) for if I woulde bee perfect, mine owne mouth ſhall condemne me, we haue bene all as an vncleane thing (ſayth Eſay) &amp; all our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes is as filthy cloutes.<note place="margin">Eſa. 64.6.</note> When yee haue done all thoſe thinges which are commanded: (ſaith our Sauiour) ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, We are vnprofitable ſeruants, wee haue done but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was our duetie to doe. And there is none righteous,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.10.</note> no not one: by the workes of the lawe ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified in his ſight, and all theſe words come from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of God. But ſeeing ye wil hardly admit the teſtimonie of Gods worde, without the witneſſe of men: go to, let vs ſee what ſay the fathers in this behalfe? I doe ſcarcely (ſaith Origen) beleeue that there can be any worke,<note place="margin">Origen. lib. 44. cap. 4.</note> that may of duetie require a reward.<note place="margin">Baſil. In Pſal. 32.</note> Baſill ſaith that hee truſteth not <pb facs="tcp:176510:90"/> in his owne good deedes, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to be iuſtified by his works, he hath the onely hope of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the mercies of GOD. And Saint Hierome,<note place="margin">Hierom, in Eſai. cap. 64.</note> If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our owne merits, we muſt be driuen to deſperation. The time will not ſerue to handle this matter at large, therefore I ende this part, beſeeching al thoſe that loue the Goſpell vnfeinedly, to take diligent heede to ſuch falſe Prophetes, as come vnto them in ſheepes clothing, faining them ſelues holy, and by their holines thinke them ſelues iuſtified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The thirde part.</head>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sed intrinſecùs ſunt lupi rapaces.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But inwardly they are rauening wolues.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Although our Engliſh popiſh Prieſtes, (that come from Rome, or elſe from Rheimes in France, <pb facs="tcp:176510:91"/> to this our natiue ſoyle) tell vs that they haue taken great labor, paſſed many daungers, yea and hazarded their owne lyues to ſaue our ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and endles miſerie, they are not to be beleeued for all theſe their brags. They are rauening wolues, they ſeeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſting confuſion both of our bodies and ſoules. What doe they teach, but falſe doctrine? doe they not ſeeke to perſuade vs to worſhip ſtocks and ſtones, yea (which is worſt) to worſhip that idole in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? They teache more, then they are well able to performe. Howe can they proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt is really &amp; tranſſubſtantially in the ſacrament of the altar? This is the effect and force of all their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: Chriſt ſpake it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayde, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> This is my body. They will haue no Tropicall figure herein to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <pb facs="tcp:176510:91"/> for that Chriſt ſayde and promiſed, that he woulde ſpeake no more in parables. This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is nought, if you ſaye, that <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> be a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. If you ſaye, that Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to vſe no more figuratiue ſpeaches, you are farre deceyued. For hee vſed a
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in this phraſe, <hi>Hic eſt calix noui Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, quem ſi biberit quiſpiam, &amp;c.</hi> This is the cup of the newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which whoſoeuer ſhall drinke, &amp;c. You knowe no man can drinke the cuppe: wherefore here is <hi>Continens pro contento,</hi> the thing conteyning, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing conteined. If Chriſt vſed a figure in this phraſe, <hi>Hic eſt calix, &amp;c.</hi> Why ſhoulde he not in like wiſe vſe a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in this phraſe, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fe</hi> The death of Chriſt is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preſent in the Sacrament. <hi>ri</hi> But the blood of Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <pb facs="tcp:176510:92"/> in the Sacrament, as his death is preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. de ſac. 4. cap. 4.</note>
                  <hi>o</hi> Therefore the precious blood of Chriſt is not really preſent in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> propoſition is proued out of Ambroſe, in his fourth booke of the Sacramentes, and fourth chapter, <hi>Vt recepiſti ſuae mortis ſimilitudinem, ſic bibis ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudinem ſui precioſi ſanguinis:</hi> As thou haſt receyued the ſimilitude of his death, ſo doeſt thou drinke the ſimilitude of his blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſ</hi> The true naturall bodie of Chriſt is placed in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>am</hi> But the true natural body of man, can bee but in one place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>is</hi> Therefore the true naturall body of Chriſt can be but in one place, and at one time in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.51. Act. 1.9.</note>The
<hi>Maior</hi> is proued thus, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus receptus eſt in coelos, &amp; ſedet <pb facs="tcp:176510:92"/> ad dexteram Dei, &amp;c.</hi> Ieſus was receiued vp into heauen, and ſitteth at the right hande of GOD the Father.<note place="margin">Matt. 26.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Pauperes ſemper habetis vobiſcum, me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò non ſemper habebitis:</hi> The poore haue you alwayes with you, but me ſhall yee not haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. <hi>Deſero mundum, &amp; eo ad patrem:</hi> I forſake the worlde, and goe to my Father.
<hi>Multi dicent in eo die, Ecce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 24.23. Mar.
13.21.</note> 
                  <hi>hic eſt Chriſtus, &amp; ecce, ibi:</hi> Many wil ſay in that day, Lo, here is Chriſt, and lo, there he is. Whatſoeuer is in many &amp; diuers places at once, is God. The body of Chriſt is not God, but a certaine creature. Therefore the body of Chriſt can not be in many places at once.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Da</hi> Euery quantitie (that is) eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body that hath le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, breadth, and thicknes, is conteined in one peculiar place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ri</hi> Chriſtes bodye hath length, <pb facs="tcp:176510:93"/> breadth and thicknes, and is a quantitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>o</hi> Therefore Chriſtes body is contained in one peculiar place.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is prooued out of Cyrill in his thirde booke of the Trinitie, pag. 245. <hi>Quic quid intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur habere corpus, hoc indubiè eſt in loco, &amp; in magnitudine &amp; in quantitate. Et ſi ſit in quantitate, euitare non poteſt circumſcriptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, hoc eſt habere ſuum locum:</hi> What thing ſoeuer is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode to haue a body, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt is in a place, in magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and in quantitie. And if it be in quantitie, then it muſt needes be in ſome peculiar place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fe</hi> No naturall body can at one and the ſame time haue contrarie and diuers qualities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ri</hi> But to be in one place local, in another not locall, in one place with quantitie, in another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie, in one place finite, in <pb facs="tcp:176510:93"/> another infinite, is to admit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary qualities to a natural body <hi>o</hi> Therefore the body of Chriſt can not be in one place locall, in another place not locall, in one place with quatitie, in another place without quantitie.</p>
               <p>We muſt ſo defend the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Chriſt, that we deſtroye not his diuinitie. If we aſſigne to Chriſtes body plurality of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wee deſtroye his diuinitie: wherefore we muſt not aſſigne to Chriſtes body pluralitie of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The myſticall ſignification that you haue imagined of your ſhewes and accidents, that the formes of breade and wine out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly repreſent the ſpirituall nouriſhing of the ſoule, is vaine and fantaſtical, without the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any auncient Doctour, or father, &amp; is confirmed only by the authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope himſelfe. For what maner of feeding is there in <pb facs="tcp:176510:94"/> theſe accidents and holy formes, or howe can that thing that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the body, repreſent vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual feeding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule? The matter is plaine ynough of it ſelfe, and needeth no cauill. The ſignification and ſubſtance of the Sacrament is to ſhew vs, how we are fed with the body of Chriſt, that is, that like as mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall bread feedeth our bodie, ſo the body of Chriſt nayled on the croſſe, embraced &amp; eaten by faith, feedeth the ſoule. The like repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is alſo made in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme: that as our body is waſhed cleane with water, ſo our ſoule is waſhed cleane w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſtes blood. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. Aug. ſaith, <hi>Niſi Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſimilitudinem quandam earum rerum, quarum Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta ſunt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berent, omninò Sacramenta non eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent:</hi> If Sacraments had not a certaine likenes and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <pb facs="tcp:176510:94"/> of the thinges whereof they be ſacraments, then in deede they were no Sacraments. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation Rabanus Maurus <hi>lib.</hi> 1.23. expoundeth thus, <hi>Quia panis corpora confirmat, ideò ille congruenter corpus Chriſti nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patur, &amp; quia vinum ſanguinem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratur in carne, ideo refertur ad ſanguinem:</hi> Becauſe (not the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents or formes of bread) but bread it ſelfe confirmeth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, therefore it is conueniently called the body of Chriſt. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wine worketh bloud in the fleſh, therfore it hath relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood. ſo likewiſe ſaith Druth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marus <hi>in Matth. cap.</hi> 28.
<hi>Vinum laetificat &amp; ſanguinem auget, &amp; ideo non inconuenienter ſanguis Chriſti per hoc ſignificatur.</hi> This I ſpeak briefly of the ſacrament of your Maſſe. Reade the olde and newe Teſtament, &amp; marke if you finde any one word directly, or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, <pb facs="tcp:176510:95"/> ſecretly, or plainely, which ſpeaketh nigh or farre, of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of your Maſſe, which is in controuerſie betweene vs. Contrariwiſe, ſee if you doe not finde therin from line to line, that Chriſt is the onely ſacrifice once offered vp for all: that there is one onely waſhing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is one only God, to be called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the onely name of Ieſus Chriſt. If you finde there the doctrines which we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, then in heart &amp; voyce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, and cry fagot &amp; fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. If not, recant then, &amp; be ſory for your errors, cry God &amp; the Queene mercy. Be ſorowful that you haue miſcalled our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady, and that you haue ſayd you would burne her bones, and burne all them of her moſt honorable counſel, that fauoured not your curſed attempts, eyther
<pb facs="tcp:176510:95"/> aliue or dead: Many of whoſe names I could rehearſe, but for certaine cauſes I wil put the firſt letter of their names. let <hi>L.</hi> ſerue the roome of a Lorde, and <hi>S.</hi> of a Knight. <hi>B.</hi> for a Biſhop. &amp;c. <hi>L.K.</hi> who is dead, <hi>L. T.</hi> who is aliue,
<hi>E. L.</hi> aliue, <hi>E. B.</hi> aliue, <hi>E. W.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, <hi>E. H. S. F. K. S. F. W. S. H. S. M. R.</hi> of <hi>L. Ar. B.</hi> of <hi>C. M. D.</hi> of <hi>C.</hi> and all ſuch as haue puniſhed (or fauoured not) their idolatrous religion. <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>L. M. D.</hi> of <hi>P. L. D.</hi> of
<hi>Yor. L. B.</hi> of <hi>Win.</hi> who is dead, <hi>B.</hi> of Saliſb.
<hi>D.</hi> of Saliſb. <hi>M. I. F.</hi> preacher at London. <hi>D. H.</hi> at Oxenforde. <hi>D. F.</hi> preacher at Cambridge, with diuers others, vpon whom you ſayd, you would ſhew no mercy. A man had neede to take heede of ſuch, as yet you are, who make men beleeue (for all this their ſpight and malice <pb facs="tcp:176510:96"/> towards their own natiue ſoyle, which they greatly wiſh to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fire, ſword, &amp; famine: this am I able to verifye by ſuch as are already conuerted to the trueth of Chriſt his Goſpell, and yet I haue omitted many things of their hatred &amp; practiſes againſt this Realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hazard their liues to ſaue our ſoules from hell, whereas in very deede, they haue wrought (as much as lieth in them) our eternall damnation, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are rauening woolues. what do they teach our Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pope is ſupreme head, &amp; that, if they will be ſaued, they muſt acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope to be ſoueraine Lord? This they teach without proofe of ſcripture. Saint Cyprian ſayth,<note place="margin">Cyprian de ſimplic. praelat. &amp; in ſenten. Epiſc. &amp; in lib. 1. Epiſt. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnum eſſe Epiſcopatum, cuius quilibet Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus tenet ſuam partem integra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine diuiſione. Praeterea nullum ſui <pb facs="tcp:176510:96"/> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poris vocaſſe aut feciſſe ſeipſum Epiſcopu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Epiſcoporum, aut tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nide ſuos ſibi ſubieciſſe ſocios.</hi> That is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is but one Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke, of which euery Byſhop holdeth his part wholy without any diuiſion. Alſo, that none of his time eyther called or made himſelfe Biſhop of Byſhops, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made through tyrannie his companions ſubiect to his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Alſo he complayning that prophane men, &amp; Schiſmatiques withdrew themſelues to the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, ſayeth that there were none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did ſo, but certeyne deſperate and wicked felowes, perſwading themſelues that the Biſhops of Affricke haue leſſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer then the Biſhop of Rome. Saint Chryſoſt. ſayeth <hi>in homil.</hi> 83. <hi>in Matt. cap.</hi> 23.
<hi>Quicunque E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum primatum in terra de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderabit, confuſionem in coelis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periet, et qui caput omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendet, <pb facs="tcp:176510:97"/> non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>putabitur in nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſeruorum Chriſti:</hi> Whoſoeuer (ſayth hee) of the Byſhops ſhall deſire ſupremacie in earth, he ſhal finde confuſion in heauen, and he that ſhal deſire to be the chiefe, he ſhall not be reputed in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſeruants of Chriſt. Loe here, the fathers of your owne Church ſay, that the Pope is not ſupreme head. As for ſcriptures, reade them throughly, and you ſhal not finde one onely text to ground your ſupremacie vpon. Wherfore (good brethren) ſeeing that your owne Doctors ſpeake againſt you, bee reconciled with me that am conuerted by Gods grace, and the induſtrie of his inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful ſir Owyn Hopton knight, the Queenes Maieſties Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of this towre of London, &amp; diuers godly preachers. Be with me reconciled, I ſay, and let vs <pb facs="tcp:176510:97"/> with one accord embrace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, and become loyall and obedient ſubiectes to our ſoueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, who ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly &amp; fauourably dealeth with vs, that, whereas (forſaking our countrey, &amp; ſubmitting our ſelues to the gouernment, or rather ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie of an Italian prieſt) wee haue deſerued the heauie wrath of our louing Queene to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with death, by our recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our treſpaſſe may be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, life graunted, &amp; wee brought into fauour againe. Wherefore, my louing brethren, (conſidering the promiſe of the bountifull cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of our gracious Queene, ready at al times to pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and traiterous offences committed againſt her Maieſtie, and the dayly labour that this right worſhipful knight ſir Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yn Hopton by name taketh, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert vs to the trueth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) <pb facs="tcp:176510:98"/> recant, recant, caſt not away wilfully your bodyes and ſoules to endleſſe paine: ſhorten not your dayes, which God hath lent you here vpon earth to do good, and make not an ende of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a bad cauſe. Allowe not the Popes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, canons of council, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of fathers, conſtitutions of men, rites and ceremonies, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and indulgences, inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſaintes, merites by workes, pilgrimage, maſſes, diriges, tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, images, pictures, reliques, altars, ſhrines, liues of fayned ſaintes, falſe miracles, viſions, dreames, fantaſies &amp; ſuch other traſhes without warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Gods worde, as it appeareth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world in your ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; Romiſh poſtils. And in fine, be not Phariſes, ſet not light by the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, forſake not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God, to folowe after the traditions of men. <hi>In vanum mihi ſeruiunt</hi> (ſaith <pb facs="tcp:176510:98"/> our ſauiour Chriſt in the Goſpell of ſaint Matthew 15.) <hi>cum nihil, aliud docent quàm traditiones ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> In vaine do they ſerue me, while they teach ſuch doctrines as are nothing but the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of men. Say not, that there be ſeuen ſacraments, ſeeing the Church of God receiueth but two, <hi>numero pauciſſima,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de doct. Chriſti. lib. 3. cap. 9. &amp; ad Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar. Epi. 118.</note> of the ſmalleſt number, (as Auguſtine writeth) which are <hi>Baptiſmus trinitatis nomine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratus, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio corporis &amp; ſanguinis ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius:</hi> Baptiſme halowed in the name of the trinitie, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of his bleſſed body and blood, figured in the olde Teſtament by the circumciſion and the paſchall lambe. Repent (my brethren) repent, and crye to God for grace and mercy. Let it neuer grieue you to returne from theſe princes of darkenes, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and the Pope. And in deede <pb facs="tcp:176510:99"/> what haue you ſeene in the court of Rome? Chriſt in exile, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt reigne in his ſtead, Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub the iudge, wolues let looſe, and the lambes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtocks. Ah good God, who ſhall deliuer the world from this oppreſſion? who ſhall gather together the ſheepe? who ſhall reproue and conuince the wicked paſtors? Shall there neuer be a limitation and ende of this intolerable miſchiefe? Howe long ſhal the Pope and his ſhaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, who haue neyther fayth, godlines nor trueth, deceiue thy poore ſheepe? Howe long ſhal the ſonne of perdition reigne ouer thy flocke? who being but a man, lifteth vp him ſelfe aboue Kings, yea aboue Angels, and aboue the heauen of heauens, and hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed men to diſpute that hee is not<note n="*" place="margin">Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius. De tranſl. C. quanto. Prohoem. Clement. Gloſſa: Papa ſtupor mundi. The Pope is the wonder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world.</note> ſimply a man, but a partaker of the diuine nature with Chriſt, and that he hath the fountaine &amp; <pb facs="tcp:176510:99"/> roote of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of Chriſt in him. To be ſhort, whereas thou, O Chriſt, haſt ſubmitted thy ſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen, earth and hell, he wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund kings, angels,<note place="margin">Gloſs. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trau. de ſede ad Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus. Diſtinct. 40. C. ſi Papa.</note> deuils &amp; all, vnder colour of the key of the word, which thou haſt deliuered to thy miniſters. I aſke, (thou being God, and made man for the ſaluation of the worlde) how it can bee that this man, which maketh himſelfe God, ſhoulde be any other, then that ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, come for the perdition of the worlde. Thou that haſt bene wounded for our tranſgreſſions, and ſmitten for our iniquities, &amp; with whoſe ſtripes we are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, gouerne, helpe, and ſuccour thy flocke: let Antichriſt periſh, and be diſcomfited by the breath of thy holy mouth, and aboliſhed by the brightneſſe of thy bleſſed &amp; wiſhed comming. Come Lorde <pb facs="tcp:176510:100"/> Ieſu, come quickly, for thy names ſake. Let all the people ſaye, Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶<hi>Jmprinted at London, by</hi> Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno 1581.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
